<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The raising of them that are fallen A discourse very profitable and beneficial to all faithfull Christians dialoguewise, betwixt a knight and a gentleman· Set foorth for the benefit and good of all such people as are afflicted eyther in minde or conscience. Written by Thomas Sauile Gent? [sic]</title>
            <author>Savile, Thomas, fl. 1595-1613.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B15648</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852002</idno>
  <idno type="VID">177877</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240867330</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 21787</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S116786</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99852002e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B15648)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177877)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1255:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The raising of them that are fallen A discourse very profitable and beneficial to all faithfull Christians dialoguewise, betwixt a knight and a gentleman· Set foorth for the benefit and good of all such people as are afflicted eyther in minde or conscience. Written by Thomas Sauile Gent? [sic]</title>
                  <author>Savile, Thomas, fl. 1595-1613.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Blower] for William Welby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [par.]⁴ A-G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The raysing of, them that are fallen.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177877:1"/>
            <p>THE RAISING OF them that are fallen.</p>
            <p>A Discourse very profitable and beneficial to all faithfull Christians Dialogue wise, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a Knight and a Gentleman Set foorth for the benefit and good of all such people as are afflicted eyther in minde or conscience.</p>
            <p>Written by Thomas Sauile Gent.</p>
            <bibl>Ioh: 10. 29.</bibl>
            <q>My Father which gaue them me is greater then all: and no man can take them out of my fathers handes.</q>
            <bibl>Apoca. 21: 7.</bibl>
            <q>Hee that ouercommeth, shall inherit all things: and I will be his God, and he shall be my Sonne.</q>
            <figure/>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed for William Welby. 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:177877:2"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of loue,</item>
               <item>2 Of thankefulnes:</item>
               <item>3 Of obedience m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ekenes and patience.</item>
               <item>4 Of afflictions generally and the
<list>
                     <item>Cause, occasion Vse, and en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e.
<list>
                           <item>proued by a famili<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>5 Of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>spayre and that it is the lot of the best beloued as <hi>Dauid Ieremy Ionah:</hi> perticular examples of our times in priuate men and women.</item>
               <item>6 The ende was euer happy and with exceeding ioyfull deliuerance vnto the chosen.</item>
               <item>7 Who is chosen, who beleeueth, with diuers other questions, touching temptations infirmities Slydings, and the Solutions for Comfort of the weake.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:177877:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous renowned, and for angel like rule ouer their owne passible tender affections in lawfull delights, more especially respected Ladies: The La: <hi>Katherine</hi> Countesse of Huntingdon, and the La: <hi>Margaret</hi> Countesse of Cumberland, and vnto Sr. <hi>Francis</hi> Hastinges, and Sr: <hi>Tho: Smith,</hi> honorable christians &amp; Knights. Tho: <hi>Sauile</hi> wisheth a continuall practise of their knowledge in the misterie of reconciliation, vntill they be compacted into the Mrs. building, and Really vnited vnto Christ, that finally they may be where he is, and haue their ioy full:</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST Honorable LLa: &amp; you worthily regarded Knights, if I did know any creatures cōparable vnto your selues, for Christian cariage and profession of Religion in the like measure, vnto those surely I would direct this my poore labor &amp; publish their examples, whereby I might direct o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>as by that star to the wisemen</hi> to take view of such shining lights as should beget a desire in the beholders, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be cōformed the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnto, euen to find the babe and glorifie the euerlasting God, who inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <note place="margin">Mat. 1.</note> the heauens in neuer ending glory: Besides this it may not bede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, but your honors fauors of diuers sorts afforded vnto me both in prison and abroad, haue iustly deserued the deepest offices of all my acknowledgments: And since the Lord hath pleased so to shake all my outward indowments as nothing therin may be found accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to present <hi>in grati animi memoriam,</hi> yet let it please you that I offer a pos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of such fragrant flowers, as I gathered in the Lords own spiritual garden of my most happy changes, amōgst which that same very censure <hi>of wisedom</hi> hath my thinkes a wonderfull soueraigne <note place="margin">wisdom. 3.</note> taste, for diuerting all infections of that contagious discontentment which doth accompany mortalitie in all men. They seeme forsaken (saith he) but their hope is full of immortalit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e: What is that? The next wordes explaine, in few thinges they bee restrained: But in many things they be rewarded: if your Ho: LLa: and you Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Knights please, to search by way of meditation, why man was
<pb facs="tcp:177877:3"/> Crea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> you wil readl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>scouer, out of your owne dayly exercises, the cause and end of mans creaton: was to giue obedience vnto the euer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uing God their Creator.</p>
            <p>The gentle long suffring preseruer of heauen and earth. <hi>Ifly vnto thee for thi very gentleues (saith a father</hi>) to bee intrated: But how <note place="margin">Chris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st.</note> shall they serue him without knowledge of his name? <hi>They erred: saith the Lord because they did not know my waies,</hi> And how shall this <note place="margin">Psal 95:</note> knowledge come, but fy Faith? and how Faith but by the worde preached? And how know they this faith, but by experience? And <note place="margin">Rom. 50. 1 Pet. 6. 7. Ro: 5. 4</note> how commeth experience but by triall, and how triall but by afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Tribulation saith Thapostle worketh patience and patience bops, &amp;c.</hi> So that affliction is as the schoole or Academy, wherin the best schollers (by rendering &amp; exercises) be appointed and prepared to <note place="margin">Thes. 3.</note> comencements of the dietie, by making familiar their receiued for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer rudiments of ordinarie discipline and changes. Now how dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tasing this in vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> world, who regorge pleasures &amp; profits, till they sursit, it (killeth not: Christ saith vnto Iohn his Disciples. The poore reciue the Gospell, which worde (<hi>Poore</hi>) in that place I thinke doth <note place="margin">Mat: 11. 29. Isaiah. 61. 1.</note> signifie the meanest sort in estate and knowledge because I find op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position in that Chapter verse 25. I thanke thee O father, that thou hast hid these thinges from the wise and prudent, and hast opened them vnto Babes: Heere seemeth a double warrant to cleere all doubts that the Gospell at it is in it selfe <hi>Sermo crucis,</hi> so affliction by weyned estate, doth most surely accompany the professors thereof, according to the measure of their desire to be changed, and the Lords purpose to shine in them: But what if the world (for all theise) doe scorne so open truth? Then do I answere, that the Iewes disputed <note place="margin">Ioh. 7. 4.</note> euen so, when they said, Why doe none of the rulers beleeue in him. Then which there was neuer any thing more grose and insulse: For <note place="margin">Ioh. 12. 42. 43.</note> the worde it selfe giueth a reason of their forsaking him (Viz) For feare to loose their places in the Sinagogue. And also because they loued the praise of men more then the praise of God. Thus hauing cleared in short, as by way of abstract, or post-script the crown of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction by so plaine and open demonstration, of the sacred W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rde, <note place="margin">Ioh. 12. 48.</note> which shall iudge at the last day, I do dedicate this poore exercise
<pb facs="tcp:177877:3"/> out of my very loue, and for a seriuice vnto you haue personages who are able to discerne the truth of that I write: wherein I offer as a motiue for all men to indure: my owne particular suffrings open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and causelessely orphaned with my many Children by violence inflicted, euen so far as if the worlde had no other president of the Lordes watch ouer his vine. (Behold saith Isaiah, I the Lord doe watch ouer my vine, yea day and night do I watch least any man assaile it,) yet that the Lord hath preserued and fed my most vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy selfe, thiese many yeeres as by Rauens, by your respected LLa: mirrours of Religion and vertue, and by that euer renowmed wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy one, the La: Anne Countesse of <hi>Warwick,</hi> as <hi>Pharoahs</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters taken me out of the Reade Arke of my Mother sinne, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me to Nurse into the schoole of afflictions and grace. This I <note place="margin">Exo. 2.</note> say may remaine as a monument for euer to openly announce the truth of his name in that hee is called wonderfull.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>An afflicted seruant of her late most sacred Maiestie Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> Tho: Sauile,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:177877:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177877:4"/>
            <head>To the Christian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Life of Christians is fitly called a way because as trauaylers do sometimes erre, sometimes stumble, sometime slide, and somtimes fall, so christians wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the plaine fields of this world, following the broad path of sinne, and forget<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the strait and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row way of piety, and grace, or else taken vniust occasion to stumble through their owne weakenes, eyther at the seueritie of diuine com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended life, or the euill examples of some other erring, and sinning brethren in the Church, or slide and srink at the afflictions which accompany vnfained deuotion and god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ines, because they cannot tarry in hopefull expectation of comfor and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>esse, vntil the clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy night of sorrowfull aduersitie be ouerpassed, and the sunne-sh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fauour of peace grace and mercie from God the Father lighten their darkenes, through <hi>Iesus Christ:</hi> or else fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>flat downe vnder the desire of the present world, ouer burdened with the distrustfull worldly cares cast vpon them by Sathan: and so lie grouelling in the myre of humaine infirmitie. Distaine the pure wedding garment which Christes Gospell hath cloathed them withall. This being the vn-auoidable lot of many of God his deare Children, it is a world to thinke how wonderfully good mindes (though weake) lye drawing their last breath, betwixt hope and feare, sleepe and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, perseuerance and oppostasie, liue perplexed: seeking and caling for direction, eyther meet with no man to set them in the right way, when they haue erred, or else by reason of their owne blindnes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not follow the right path they are set in, hauing no guides to holde them by the hand, or if they haue stumbled, there is no man that will remoue the block out of their way, or lift vp their weake legges of knowledge and vnderstanding ouer that daunger, neyther stay their sliding, comfor them sorrowing, vpholde them salling, or raise them vp beeing flat on their backes, in worldly and humaine weakenes Thou shalt therefore finde in this succeeding Treatise, a continuall demonstration of this misery, and a faithfull and strong hand to help thee in all these aduersities, so that by good vse it may proue as good to thy soule, as the angell that brought Poter out of prison, loosing his bands and opening the yron gates, holding fast
<pb facs="tcp:177877:5"/> the eyes of all the watchmen, till hee was perfectly deliuered and recouered from bodily thraldome: Onely I pray God that no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, shame disdaine, incredulitie, labour or temptation, whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, hinder thy desired recouery, that readest and wisliest the day of thine owne and Churches safety, foretold by the Prophet <hi>Ioel, Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem shalbe all holy and the strangers shall passe by her no more,</hi> and I wish that thou maist more deepely affect this Treatise, because the author doth professe himselfe to bee no scholler, nor writing from conference or counsell with any, but being recouered with variety of heauy f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elinges in his smarting indured changes, <hi>as that same calling (spoken of (by</hi> Christ Iesus <hi>before Magistrates. Math: 10. Did humbly beseech the Lord for help,</hi> Wherevpon the writ that which was in the very instant ministred vnto him, euen the secret hidden Wisedome, &amp; inestimable worth of the mistery in afflictions which the Angels de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to behold. 1 Pet: 1. 12: So manifesting vnto the world, that the corrections of the meeke, induring by patience, and silence, are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer accompanied with that vpholding, illuminating, and instruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing staffe and grace of God, euen to make them partakers of his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry holines, by sence of a continuall discipation of hindrances, and streaming comfort ministred vnto them in due season, warranted by the last writing of the worde. Reuel: 22. 1. 2. 3. <hi>Behold there shal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be no more curse, But the throwne of God and the Lambe, shalbe in the viuer of pure Water, and his seruant stall serue him.</hi> Euen so Amen, Come Lord Iesus quickly</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. L.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:177877:5"/>
            <head>The Raysing of, them that are fallen</head>
            <p>K <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR I thanke you: you are as good as your promise, for that you said you would not be long from me. <hi>G</hi> Yt is true Sir, neyther that I would forget you in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence. K. And haue you remembred me? <hi>G.</hi> Yees indeede, euen so deeply, as to taxe my selfe blame-worthy, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God &amp; man, for neglect of duty vnto you euen in the highest degree. K. what in the conference? <hi>G.</hi> Yees in good earnest. K How should that be? Gent: Nay how should it not be? that we who hauing recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued experience by the present assisting grace of God, to make vs wade through such a red sea of prophane &amp; carnall humors opening way to find our corruptions, and the redresse thereof: nay and to feele his presence, by wonderfull workes sealed with the teares of our eyes, in the assured sweetenes of his truth and worde not onely <hi>To be a sauor of life vnto vs, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> selfe in heath, &amp; light in darknes,</hi> I say who wold not for a fauor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> high prlee haue giuen thankes, &amp; in aged themselues by open bond of acknowledgment, vnto a lasting vow of preparation, and obedience whiles they liued? K. why? we did so: G. that we did not: K. I proue we did by the example of the <hi>Hebrew seruant</hi> Ex. <hi>the xxi.</hi> G. I thinke no such thing: that was spoken and remembred to our shame and by way of conuincing our open default for not doing as he did, and he shall witnes against vs. K. I thought otherwise: G. no no, there vpon &amp; by that very example we should haue vnfoulded our perticular open wants in the feelings of receiued grace, and haue made a perticular
<pb facs="tcp:177877:6"/> page (by way of conference) how we should escape that we were not found short of the poore Hebrews example? wee should haue coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all our faculties to giue their consent how we might oblige our selues in an irre-vocable rule of holy labor and strife for obedience in our selues, to excite others and so second the poore. Hebrewes example, to goe to the post of Gods lawe and there in our owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons designed, to be registred amongst those ho hauing remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the mastres demaund, <hi>To loue him withall our harts soules and spirits,</hi> haue offred our fealty vnto his sacred segniorye and engaged our selues perpetually to erect alters to celebrate his glory, goodnes, and loue, whilest we liued K. Indeed but you are to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stere in this point for we did acknowledg the goodnes of God as our happy Phisition, and wee confessed the admiration of his loue &amp;c. G. very true but who offred or payed his required fee? wee resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the begger? who receiuing almes wil blesse, and giue good words but let the Iustice enioyne him to lay away his roging walkes, then will he mutyne and be discontented; and tell me Sir. (for I would deale plainely with you) did we either by prayer, or offred vow vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, or any way oblige our selues, to be thankeful in the former exercise as touched with the open power, and presence of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy therein. K. no truly G. why then therein wee are short wee should haue vnfoulded his mercyes <hi>euen to make vs astonied</hi> Eze. 36. we should haue repudiated the sway of our earnalitie: we should haue embraced grace &amp; discarded our natural man by so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne diource; and entred into our rest vpō a new enacted couenant of more holy obedience, by taking vowe euen for all the dayes of our life: we should haue enioyned these entraled affections of our vnto vanity, to take pleasure &amp; their whole dilight in following the example of Dauid who hauing wōderfuly prouoked the Lord: (euen so far as the Lord turned away from him) wherevpon hee felt the horror of euerlasting death: yet when God was pleased to giue him but one flash of his mercy, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> very first words that he spok (asitwere) in open acknowledgement and tendred obediēce for fauor received was to abandon all the companions of vanity and sinne <hi>Away from mor all yée workers of Iniquity &amp;c.</hi> Psalme 6. 8.
<pb facs="tcp:177877:6"/> and for his owne person what heauie impositions hee enioynēd to make all former vanities and sinne distasting vnto him, <hi>reade yée ite</hi> 131. <hi>Psal.</hi> See there by playne vowe and obtestacion, hee doth make a couenant with the Lord; <hi>that he will not enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his house, nor come vpon his pallet, nor giue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rye to his eyes, nor rest to his eye-lids, vntill he had found ont a place for a habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation sor the mighty God of Jacob:</hi> and not being thus satisfied but still dwelling vpon the contemplation of so great receiued mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, doth sommon all the faculties of his soule and spirit by way of recount, or demaund, <hi>what he should giue againe to the Lord</hi> &amp;c. <note place="margin">Psal. 116. 12. 13</note> &amp; knowing that the only enemy against his obedince would be the sway of nature he did resolue, and iudicially determine to take vp and engage himselfe vnto <hi>the wholesome cup of of Gods afflictions, and giue thankes vnto the name of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for his thankfulnes to men read yee <hi>the 2 of Samuel the 9. and 10. chapters,</hi> and there yee shall finde a myrrour for all good natures to take pleasure in: neuer to forget a fauour receiued in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction and distresse. K. good Lord be all these things needfull? G. why doe yee doubt sweet Knight? I fare me you haue forgotten much for was it not agreed (as a speciall truth) <hi>that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> violence must</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 12.</note>
               <hi>be maintayned for the kingdome: and that none but they continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> that violence against customes, and all natures serpintine, alure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments should receiue the Gospell and kingdome? K. yes I confesse: G. why thē I pray you tell me wherin we haue in any one perticular imitated those golden examples of <hi>Dauid?</hi> what exercise of violence we haue charged our selues withall? that the Lord <hi>Who hath made vs so wonder at his mercyes,</hi> might but see vs resigne our wills <hi>to the knocking spirit</hi> who laboreth to inuest vs into the sanctuarie, by giuing vs some change, and renewednes from our former vanityes, by conducting vs into all truth, I confesse for my part none at all. G. see then my sweet hart how rawly I did leaue you, which I sorrow and morne for, that Sathan should enter vpon you but halfe prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and yet did presage vnto you in the former discourse, that cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly Sathan would be very busye with you, by occasion of your former conuersing which though you affect not as formerly, yet
<pb facs="tcp:177877:7"/> many heauy tēptations would arise &amp; require a mighty recistance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst which the remembrance of a solemn vow, deuoted vnto the Lord: Would haue bene a great bar &amp; Obsta: but why do you study my Kni? K. Indeed I haue sinned since your departure. G. the more pitty I feared it, &amp; so haue I done with you, our iust penalties succee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our cōmon default, but <hi>I</hi> hope neyther of vs do iy in our sli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, neither y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wee be without purpose to stand more strongly by the exeprience of this fall: K <hi>I</hi> hope so: but it was a happy thing you came againe for I had almost forgot all: G. well let vs both render obedyence &amp; thanks to our glorious God, who passing byso grosse a default on both parts: yet ret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rneth in due time, &amp; hauing appointed <hi>A reuhering day shortly</hi> calleth vs to confer togither to make our opē acknowledgments of our wants, in omitting our thanks, though we be short of the bette Schollers who bringes obedience in their gripps, but alas my Knight haue you sinned since we parted in your ancient predomināt sin? K. Not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> worst way: but I haue frequented vaine cōpany &amp; endured vnreformed speeches excesses, &amp; othes to my great vnrest G. But did they vnrest you? K. yes y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lord knoweth? G: why thē you pluck at lilly out of the Mrs. garden spoken of in our former exercise of prisoners conference; but alack why did you yeeld? K The Lord doth know I could not chose for since my estate was disputed, &amp; indeed razed, &amp; my fortune translated, I haue had no comunity with those men whose company I desired, and by whose example I should haue bene bettered, but haue dwelt in Zodam &amp; conuersed in Gomorrah G. The more pitty sweet hart: al this you confesse the medicine &amp; most iust penalty and soffraine smart for recuring your youth and time mispent doe you not? K. O yes, yes with all my hart. G. But tell me what did you meane by this word fortune? you know the Prophet sayth <hi>all my times and changes, are in thy hands O Lord Psal</hi> 35. K. Fortune is a foolery, and receiued fantasticall speech, for I beleeue no such matter, <hi>a sparow falleth not without Gods prouidence Math: 10: Luke 12, the Lord beholdeth from heauen Psal:</hi> 33 53. G: I thanke you Sir griue not though I search you deepe, the rather because you may stand more warily heareafter, and abandon vnreformed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyes.
<pb facs="tcp:177877:7"/> K. how should I? for besides I do not know where to ly but by their help, so Indeede I am indebted vnto them. G. But you will giue me leaue to loue you euen very much will you not? K: O yes I stand the better by your loue, &amp; desire in Gods fauor. G. Then be plaine with me, was it meere extremity y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> driue you into this compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, or (in singlenes) some disposition out of your former weakenes? I would discouer <hi>snorting <hi>Ionah</hi>
               </hi> in your owne priuitys, that you might hate it with a perfect hatred K. Sir. I embrace your loue, &amp; care, and will deale plainely with you? I had a great weakenes in bearing their scornefull eyes, and the wordsof their abiection that did heauily fall vpon me, and my state being weake, I desired to make my selfe tollerable amongst them, and so did not respect so much the Lords knoweth what I should haue done in respect of former vowes as how to make my selfe sociable amongst them: G. The more pity well, stand still vpon your former experiences, and haue your acknowledgments in your hand against your selfe, and by the Lords leaue, the storme shal vanish. K. Alas Sir, I do know I do many thinges, which though not simply euill in themselues, yet vnto me they be sin, because I doe thereby <hi>scatter abroad, and do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not gather with the saynts,</hi> and all this by the long indured con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of my abiected estate, which also I confesse for an extreame weakenes, <hi>for who repaireth his condition, by walking inordinar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? or who is betteres by the vnreformed sway of his desires? let him speak that liueth but returneth sad; fearefull lodned with dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction and heauy feare</hi> from such a banquet of insolency and sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet and heareupon it is, that I pray the Lord be more spedy for my repayre, to help me out of these heauy endurings: alas why will not the Lord heare and help me when I desire nothing but strength to resist his enemy? G. Then you think y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Sathans hand is in your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities, K. yes so far as God will: but why hath Sathan intrest in my desires which bothe Lords creations G. <hi>Nay rather how should he not desire to destroy them? because they be Gods crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</hi> for if they were ours he would not enuy thē, beside this you may not demaūd why the Lord doth any thing for he doth nothing but in all loue and compassion vnto vs: you know how we hanged
<pb facs="tcp:177877:8"/> vpon him &amp; held him <hi>with Jacob,</hi> &amp; how sweetly he did satisfy vs in all things: &amp; we haue fayled with him in al things, let y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> patience and praise be his, &amp; shame &amp; rebuke be ours, <hi>he only giueth Sathan leaue to make the fire whereby we shall be fined and made more acceptable to him, but</hi> mee thinks you looke dead, and heauy min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded I pray thee faynt at nothing, for all the wayes of the Lord <hi>are mercy truth, &amp; compassion, streaming strength, &amp; swéetues, in all our distresses:</hi> K: This is the matter y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> woundeth me I haue solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Lord in a particuler fraylty these xx. yeeres, and he will not heare me: G. is that your gratest griefe? truly this is no griefe at all if you attend stil in weldoing &amp; recisting euil, it seemeth y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lord is disposed to haue your continual faithful watch in this quarter of the but taile, K I disgest not this, G: well then I will fill your gripps full of gladnes euen from this your sorrow you say you haue prayed 20. yeeres <hi>so did <hi>Abraham Isack &amp; Iacob</hi>
               </hi> so did <hi>Moses 40. yeres <hi>&amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers others of the patriarkes</hi>
               </hi> what if the Lord wil haue your fayth monumented &amp; registred with theirs for cōstant enduring, is this no recōpence of a smal forborne fading liberty of the flesh by designed combat with Sathan? but behold my poore soule tel mee but one thing to assure thy hart y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> God hath bene, and is with thee <hi>who hath preserued thée this 20. yeares that Sathan had neuer power to touch a hayrs of thy dead?</hi> In this fearefull encounter continued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the prince of the ayre, that roring, raging, walking watching Lyon, whose mallice to preuent the Lord doth a vow, <hi>That he will watch continually, yea night &amp; day will he watch, loast Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>than assayle thee:</hi> I <hi>sayah</hi> 27. K: It is very pretily applied you silence me with a sweet clap vpon the lippes, to preuent my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinings, and make me smother my foolish words, for indeede this preseruation of the Lord assureth, that howsoeuer our selues and sacrifices be faulty and vnpure, yet he is not iealous ouer vs and them, but euen passeth by our spots and deformities, both in the matter and manner of our broken presents before him, as that sweet hony sweet meekenes of Christ Iesus <hi>in the 7. of <hi>Luke:</hi> When the poore besotted Elders of Jerusalem came to intreat him for the Centurious seruant, and they plead his desarts,
<pb facs="tcp:177877:8"/> and that he was worthy:</hi> A more filthy incence then which, they could not haue casten in the innocent Lambes nostrils, yet hee agreeth &amp; goeth to satisfie them: See sweet hart what any man loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth by attending, the Lords leysure, K: Indeede I thanke you Sir, you speake as hauing authoritie G: But are yee well? and shall wee reason a little more? K: with all my very hart G: enlarge this priuity of sences for I am dull and dead, and vncapable of good things. K: I learne it of you, that beeing resigned vnto the Lord he will giue vs meekenes, <hi>whereby we shall euen receiue the sacrets of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell and enioy the earth:</hi> Wee shall also receiue patience, inuesting vs into our rest, bringing vs crucified vnto the world and the world to vs: Thirdly we shall possesse our soules in the quiet fruit of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes: and all this from rendring our obedience by the practise of our restrayned wils, in our resolute violence for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> kingdome. G: It is very sweetly spoken K: but how feele you? G: nothing well, for I must needs tell you since our former Conference concluded, I haue beene wonderfully wounded in hart and mind K: Was your griefe for outward or inward wants? G: ah sweet hart thou art a faithfull Phisitian indeede: it was for matters of the world, as an occasion: but giuing liberty vnto my sences was the foundation, I thinke so for to be griuedd for want of required duties is no sin: but to consult with our affections is very dangerous; I know the counsels of the Lord are like vnto a great depth, and no reason to be enquired of, but thus farre I proceede against my selfe out of my priuties G: but how may you bee so vncomfortable vnto my weake estate? you will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware that you cast not downe that which by the grace of God you haue builded in me? G: no it is the Lords building, and he will maintaine it, howsoeuer hee dispose of my sinfull estate: I am clothed with a wonderfull thick muddy, benummednes, as though there were no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dresse for me in heauen, or earth: K: I cannot tell what to say to you, what is your owne opinion,? G: Sir it is my auncient louing companion, which hath beene long from mee: <hi>And I reioyce to haue it, but faint to indure it: I means my trembling:</hi> And yet the Lord sheweth me euen by you, both the cause, vse, and ende: K: I pray you speake on: G: it is very true
<pb facs="tcp:177877:9"/> my long indurings haue beene such, and my generall abiections so infestred with the companions of pouerty, as I no sooner heare of some dispatch but I enter straight into an ouer wiening per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasion of vanity, by reason of my brokennes, and the Lord seeth that thereby I communicate my selfe with the multitude (as a man come out of a strange country,) beateth mee home againe, and therevpon I sit downe and sorrow not for my smart, but that my very weakned sence should let go hold of the violence which I had deuoted vnto the Lord in all changes thus hauing grieued my gratious Lord who hath not denyed me any fauour, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned in due time in all my distresses, and I haue made a ship wrack of all his fauours, wherevpon hee hath pleased to set be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mee, the worst of all my estates: all my enterprises broken: and my ends preuented with preiudice: and to let you and the world know it, I write no dreame or fable, thus it was: The credit of my booke drawne vp, <hi>by my euer sweet late gratious renowned Mistris Queene Elizabeth hath</hi> beene long my supply for maintenance, and a councellor great not knowing my weake estate hauing my booke in his hands departed away: So my hope of dispatch frustrate, my booke shut vp, my debts were great vpon scores, to such as did neede as much as my selfe, and thus not only disabled to discharge that was past, but how to maintaine my selfe till Tearme, I appealed vnto others, and offred all interest of my suite, onely to bee supplied for my credit and maintenance till his returne.</p>
            <p>These men I found distracted with their owne particular wants; so as certainty were to bee expected, but euen in my best per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swasions, all my hopes fall broken which I did expect: Also hee that loued me, and I honoured him more then any man, was so pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stered with paying other mens debts as he left both my reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and state out of his care, wherevpon a generall darkenesse did srprize all my faculties, seeing both my credit and religion exposed to open scorne and scandall: Therevpon I fell into the trembling of the hart astonishment of sences, and no great appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension of deliuerance, for my foolishnes and ouerweening was
<pb facs="tcp:177877:9"/> still in my sight: herein I continewed some dayes and nights after which those beames, which forerun the glory of the sunne did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, and gaue me some light intimating that my feare ought not vtterly to discorage my hope since I did know how weake I had beene in apprehending a show of my desired lyberty, but rather<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n ought to reioyse that I find my selfe by this grations fauour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke asured I should not both loose the Lords care ouer my life and his Gods blessings in my particular labours, will ye see my knight? Nay will the world see and bee astonied? Heerevpon I did arise and was prety well, and am still as well as am I sit for: <hi>For the Lordis my shepheard, his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od, his staffe, and healing afflictions are mine,</hi> and blessed be his will, and nothing but wo vnto my will, K: Sir I confesse that I haue receiued strength by you, and that I haue neyther strength nor faculty, that I would not pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er out, for your ease and redresse: That heauy plight affecteth me euen within, and with indigniteie I speake it, it is pitty that a man of your place, imployment, christian care, and loue of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters euery way, should be thus orphaned both in the Church and common wealth, G: No such matter Sir, I haue beene wronged strangely: neither by Church nor common wealth; on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for my tryall, he the lord hath giuen my outward estate into the hands of oppressors and mercy lesse men, to distresse me by cause<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse cruetly, and in recompence of this, he hath sent vnto me <hi>as those Rauens to <hi>Elyah</hi>
               </hi> the most worthy Ministers of his worde, mearestrangers vnto me: &amp; these haue both reliued me in prison, and deliuered me from the prison, and comforted mee abroad: out of your owne wants: <hi>So righteous and equall is the Lord in all his designes: and holy is his name,</hi> will you now proceede sweete Knight? K: yes indeede like a souldier plainely, and yet desire to walke within the limit of softnes which you haue taught me: G. The Lord euen Iesus open all your faculties, that you may speake not onely for my Better standing, but many others: K: Amen: Sir you know we souldiers hauing a seruice in hand, make many surueyes, in our attempts, as counsell of armes decreeth: we
<pb facs="tcp:177877:10"/> view the grounds, the woods, the waters, the hils, and the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys, where to find desired aduantage and oppertunitie, for plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our forces, eyther for defence, or offence now: Yf we haue any successe in part wee thinke our selues prety well and reioyce: but admit we loose all our enterprises, all charges, and a number of our men, poore soules that gaue the aduenture, are we discora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged? no, no: wee be inflamed with indignitie, and resolute zeale, we put vpon vs vertuous and valorous mindes, to affect our enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prises, anp wee will tarry and see the end till the last man: for we know if wee can continew, time will by fire, famine, or sword, worke the conclusion plausible, (and note my Gent) <hi>that this ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice is not against a mercifull Lord, as we attend in our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular suffring,</hi> but against a tyrant that desireth to drinke vp all our bloods in cup: Againe our successes in armes bee vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, <hi>but the soules of the afflicted be in the handes of God, and their expected issues most blessed,</hi> from a most mercyfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, and therefore let vs neuer shrinke, neuer be weary, but endure, surey, hope, deuise, practise, attempt, all good meanes for our strength and standing, and then behold the oddes.</p>
            <p>Yf we fall in afflictions, we fall into <hi>The</hi> Mrs <hi>armes, his mercy doth compasse vs, he looketh from heauen for our safty, and what should</hi> discorage vs? they that attend <hi>vpon the Lord sayth <hi>Esayh</hi> 40. they shall renewe their strength, their winges shalbe as the wings of the Eagles: they shall not be wearyned in their iourney, nor faynt in their way. <hi>Scaelah</hi>
               </hi> G. I beseech you, in all our loues that you speake still vnto me, I delight to heare you, resemble afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with armes for certaynely affliction is a violent warlike assault vpon the state of mortallity, as is sufficiently proued by that place of <hi>Isuah 20 (viz) <hi>y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shalt forget the shame of thy youth, &amp; the reproch of thy widdowhood:</hi>
               </hi> as though he should haue sayd, those few spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallots are most heauy, and therefore require a more spedy redresse K. Indeed my Gentleman I am not prepared neyther able as I should be enlarged, for apprehending many excelent things touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing afflictions: <hi>as the cause to be the only loue of God: the occasion to be our brusing and sinne: the vse that we vow more holy obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb facs="tcp:177877:10"/> the end that we be healed and enriched thereby:</hi> An old exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cised souldier would fit this excellently, with a simile of armes G: Sweet Knight speake still vnto me, and I will giue you the right hand of felowship, both in arme, and in sperituall exercises, for your speeches haue grace and maiesty like a souldier compleat in his own skill and resolution: K. Indeede I would do any thing for you, as you haue layd downe your hart vnto sorrow for mee, but you wil pardon, for indeede I am wonderfull weake, G: you may bee sure God will pardon you, I and will doe you ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, K: Indeede my G: I haue some enlargement of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thinges fallen vnto me, and must goe into the warres and doe confesse I am not as I was, when your loue, care, and desires, did force teares out of my fast boulted hart. In witnesse of my misery, yet I woulde I had a fountayne to powre out for your ease, and lightning any way: G. euen for your owne Crowne, and my Peace, let mee write before you goe, howe you haue layd vp these same perticulars of afflictions: The cause: The occasion: Vse: And ende by resemblance with warres: K: Yt is your turne to apply vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your selfe, thiges offered to your consideration: G: But when did I leaue you so? What if my astonishment, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling doe so possesse mee, as to depriue mee of feeling, and power, will youd eny the hand of your strength vnto mee? K: No indeede if I doe, my hand forget his office vnto my selfe: Gent: I pray you speake my sweete Knight, K: Indeede my men stay for mee, G: Grieue mee not in denying comfort vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee where my care hath beene extended and racked for you, K: No, by no meanes, I will rather loose the service, and since you will needes haue mee speake out of my Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes array, so farre differing from the Prions, I will speake as a Captayne, to your fower poyntes, worthy note in the question of affliction G: Good sweete hart speake vnto my afflicted minde, the worde of purity and poewr, and know you speake vnto the Lord, euen in the face of his annoynted: <hi>And forget not that his hart will reioyes, and his reynes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,
<pb facs="tcp:177877:11"/> &amp; to heare you speake righteous things</hi> Pro: 23 K. now my Gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ince you will haue one prepare by way of diuerting from the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of my seruice me thinks a fitter preparation by way of example in this proiect of affliction) cannot be found then from the camp: for if a man my seruant whome I loue be wounded (as euery man is by sinne) then I presently send for a Surgion, now his wound is not grieuous in sence at the time of the wound receiued neither doth he complayne but I care for him in my loue: for who feeleth a hurt in sight? or the danger of a shot in the instant when the mind is distracted, the blud set on fire, and the irefull affections of the spirit, depriued all outward sence for the time as in a diuerse occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion <hi>Salamon</hi> sayeth <hi>the strength of the spirit sustayneth and reui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoth the outware sences:</hi> So in the exercises of sinne for the instant plausible and pleasant, but when out afflictious returne vnto the law, as the souldier into the camp, then all is fore, stack, grieuious, and vntestfull then he must be searched with instruments, and tents, and diuers appliances haply very painefully: Sathan is the wounder, he still alureth nay inforseth to breach of obedyence in the open decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red will of our God, as ready at euery corner to wound. The Lord: seeing his seruant thus wounded in keeping his possession of his hart, he presently sendeth for his Phisitian affliction, what is the property of this Phisitian affliction? <hi>his property is to make vs tel our wound truly and how as we became hurt, and that we desired to be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with any paynes in the world, nay this Phisitian affliction will teach and inforce to try our very priuityes, and thoughts to confessed al to the Mr. y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> we may be soundly healed</hi> Psal. 33 Eccel. 27. 5. Pro. 24. 21: and 17. Lo thus far my G. the occasion: out of the captaynes loue he hath the healing Phisitian: for the vse the souldier rebuked and beaten by heady and vnwarranted aduenture to go out of aray, without his captaynes priuety confesseth and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be remitted, and healed and he will all his life long after serue him more carefully and in sobernes: he will loue his captayne and beware of heady rash aduerntureses after, &amp; euer haue in his hand &amp; hart the loue and regard of this healing cōmander, and so trayned in temperance &amp; restraint by applauding his happy deliueraunce and
<pb facs="tcp:177877:11"/> recuring, shal grow delightful vnto his Captayne, &amp; what shalbe the end? euen this: he is healed his credit &amp; charge enlarged, his whole e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state re-established, for his cōmanders designed, groweth an expert man, able to be leader &amp; trainer of others in seruice of highest waight &amp; continuing cōstant in his deuoted seruice, dyeth with some, and is buryed in his colors: right so in the spirtua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l conslicts a mā approued &amp; made wise by Gods chastisemēts, is called and prepared for touch seruice, both for his owne person: example &amp; training of others, and haply to lose his life for keeping possession for his Mr. whose pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it shal be registred with a holy memory among the saints: so ye see my Go: for hast I make haply large speed, &amp; short sence, but vnto you it is for whō I owe my very selfe, &amp; do giue you a slower of your owne tree if I haue failed tel me before I go. G: That is to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mater for you haue comforted me, as you haue receiued very faythfully and I pray you sweet Kn, let me heare you speake of obedyence a little before you go, euen to bind all my seruice vnto you, and for more gayne <hi>from our reciprocall profiting by our mutuall layth,</hi> for indeed I <note place="margin">Rom: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> am weake in some poynts perswaded vnto you: tel me therefore how obedyence may be resēbled with armes vnto him who demaundeth nothing but loue, and a resign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d will for his whole Kingdome: K: Why will ye charge me thus, being new entred into the Camp. G. Best of al that you may carry y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wil of God as your ensigne chang the truth whereof you haue vnfoulded vnto others for your last farwell: K. Since you wil haue vnfoulded vnto others for your last farwell: K. Since you wil haue it so, as I conceiue raptim, I take obedience, to be as you haue described it, not only our wil resigned but also an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dustrious &amp; vtter bestripping of nature: <hi>Thoou shalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy hart &amp;c. and thy neighbor as thy selfe:</hi> Now because I would be gone to avoyde all suspition of impossibilities, and difficulty in this commaund wee must euer in all our vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences and constant aduentures, <hi>Carry Christ Jesusi for our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signe in our Helmet who is the stabilitie, accomplishment, ends, and concellor, of the Lawe.</hi> G. How can hee bee sayd to bee the stabilitie: Who abrogateth 3. K. you meane not that I should go this night I perceiue. G. not with my will. K. wel to your question <hi>Christ is y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> stabilitie of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Law because he hath giuē obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:177877:12"/> vnto it, and a voweth it righteous,</hi> also because hee payd the extreamest price for satisfaction of all required dutyes in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: by the very letter thereof, and hauing rendred whatsoeuer is due thereby hath cancelled it: Now obedience is the record, whereby euery man shall know, <hi>Whether it be cancelled for him or no:</hi> Was it not then euen in very reason equall that the Lord <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah</hi> should lay a heauy yoake vpon the posteriity of disobedient <hi>Adam,</hi> who so quickly made sale of the whole garden wherein he was shriued in righteousnes and holynes, &amp; who kept the watch then? who made continuall claime then? and least wee also should fal into the same prouocation, &amp; be concluded in the penalty, it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed him to establish this Law, <hi>which if any man wil rather choose to keepe than walk in obedience: well: he shall liue by the Law: but for an euer sure anchor the lamb proclaimeth, if any man will seru</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12.</note>
               <hi>me, let him forsake himselfe, and take vp his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rosse &amp; follow me, &amp; if any man loue me him will my father honor:</hi> Ioh: 12, 20. Here is the crowne of happy obedyence? so that in vs remayneth nothing but that we keepe our wils, free from consent of euill, and the rest is fulfilled: G: It is not so smala matter as you make it, for I am sure you alow that concupicence, in very thought is sinne, K: I doe so in the generall censure of our mortality, wherein all is concluded vnder sin, to magnify the grace and free gift of God: but no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, &amp; that which I speake I had it from you. G. it is such a sinne though sleeping as (if imputed) is dammable K. that same it is well added, so doth the Lord speake out of his own tender affection vnto Ephraim, <hi>Ier. 32. <hi>If I can forget my selfe, or if the heauens can be spanned, the said numbred or the seas fadomed? then wil I fails my couenant with Israell:</hi>
               </hi> The like speech hee hath in the 54. of <hi>Isaiah. <hi>If I can bring the waters agayne to drowne the world then I wil fayle and forsake the afflicted</hi> Iacob:</hi> G. you pass e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer too slightly K: You haue abused me the more, for I write no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what I haue receiued from the Lord by you: G: I say the sin of cogitation, though sleeping is a foule sinne: K: So say I? what then? G: Then I say the holy Ghost dwelleth not in a foule hart: K: Where doth he dwel then? <hi>For the Apostle sayth, that in him there
<pb facs="tcp:177877:12"/> dwelleth no good things:</hi> Ro: 7. <hi>and that there is neyther will nor deede in him to goodnes,</hi> Phi. 3: <hi>and the prophet</hi> Ier: <hi>sayes the hart is deceitfull and wicked, aboue all things who knoweth it,</hi> Iere: 17. 9. <hi>and in the 6 of</hi> Gen: <hi>it is said that the very preouarication and secret cogitation of mans hart, is altogether euill from the beginning how say you now, my Gent?</hi> Ge I pray you reconcile the places: K: Yee very easly The Prophet sayth, Psal: 66. <hi>Is I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard wickednes in my hart, too Lord will not heare me: that if I entertayne and dwell vpon wickednes to take helight in it:</hi> So not my foule heart, but the delight of my will maketh mee distast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before God: G: But I cannot abandon vnrighteous thoughts and cogitations, no not sleeping and you know the Apostle enioyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth our very thoughts to be cleane, K: There is the tryal of our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyence, in labouring still, and patiently enduring the penalty of our rebellious descent: he perswadeth only, enioyneth no such estate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any man: he doth not charge vs with our sleeping, with ourwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and wandring cogitations: G. But what remedy for this state, is there no help? K: I returne your owne answere to the like question redresse there is, remedy none: G: how is that? K: truely wee must hold in all our wayes a moderation of dyet, and restraynt in all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thinges: and call instantly vpon Christ Iesus, it is of the nature of those Diuels which will not be cast out, <hi>but by Fasting &amp; Prayer.</hi> Which doe help very much against the violent assaults of sinne: but cogitation thoughts decyeth onealy by attending, instantly vpon the Sonne of God: and that I may confirme all my opinions, according to your desire: from the presidents of Armes: If I charge my man for a watch in my quarter, and hee by violence is affayled to betray me, &amp; the enemy, doth inforce him to Parley with him, and he taketh time to giue answere, and in the night following dreameth that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lrayeth me: Shall I for that dreame take and execute him as a Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor? no no, I will rather alow his discretion, to entertayne them that he may vnfold, and discourse still the purpose of their plots, and bee better able to preuent them by this expereince, so long as Treason is not in his hart: And no lesse will the Lord make the very assaults of sinne; profitable vnto vs, by illuminating our mindes to discouer
<pb facs="tcp:177877:13"/> their ends, and we shall giue more glory vnto his grace, and stand more strictly by a lamentable view of our former slydingers: G: I pray you tell mee how this is to resist the beginning, and abandon vnreformed societyes? K. is it true? I pray you who is waspish now? Indeed you thinke you haue me at a nonplus, but I will vse this, your obiection as a motyue to stir vp my facultyes to finde out sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for you: Therefore thus: you know the proportion was produced from your conceaued griefes for dreames, and sleeping cogitations, which I thinke I answered fitly from the dreame of my seruant, comming from Parley with the enemye, for that further leaue, wherein I giue liberty of parlaus I did restrayne it, if his hart befree, so I say according to the truth of a mans hart, it is sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply not vnlawfull to admyt contemplation, of sinfull cogitations, neyther to haue conference with sinners, for thereby hee may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a deeper experience, of their loathsome ends: and where it is said wee must resist, beginnings it is counsell vnto men, weake and frayle by their owne inherent dispositions, and inlining to sinne: so I thinke the proportion is cleared in euery branch, and euery iust suspition in the rest of my example: and so my auncient louer and Master I say, <hi>quid tuum igitur.</hi> The state of the heart and will is all in the whole: for as parley with an enemie is lawfull for a trusty ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uant, so if he bee vnsound, al is vnlawfull ab initio: G. my wants and woes be heauy vnto me, but gaynfull vnto you, for now you see how the Lord: hath loued you to make you so profit, as that you <hi>are able to comfort others with that which you haue receiued,</hi> see also the truth of that I sayd vnto you how little assurance any man hath of his standing, for many fearefull tentation haue sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed all my feelings, since I see you before now: and I do thanke the Lord that I do se his watering vpon our conference: for it ioyeth my very hart to heare you speake: and thus do I rececapitulat your speeches for they be pure gold: you conclude, that the Lord deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our loues, with all our harts and spirits, and our neighbours as our selues doth sommon all the facultyes of our minde and spirit vnto the whole obedience of his declared will, euen so farre as to labor for purity of thoughts to abridge our desired liberty of
<pb facs="tcp:177877:13"/> vaine wordes company and sinfull exercises. K. Now truely you haue spoken like a Mr. and exceeding my capacitie, prudeut cause for breuity: I would I had in such manner conceaued and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by your happy enlargements vnto me, on heauenly things. G: Well sir I thanke you now the Lord be with you. K. Nay as sure as I liue I wil neuer speake last, whiles you may speake for I am vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furnished in one great and dangerous poynt to bee graced in fight and armes which may and is, likely to fall vpon me.</p>
            <p>K. Mee thinkes in this matter of obedience, you doe like mee lesse then all the rest: G: No maruell: for I told you that heerein consisted the accomplishment of all our whole righteousnes, and holy conformitie vn to the Lambe, in shewing our lights by renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed wayes, to gloryfie God. K. This is wonderfull to heare you of this opynion that I must passe by the Lawe for my saluation: G: Your owne wordes confound you, <hi>For by Christ Jesus you passe it indeede, whereas otherwise you should stick fast Eternally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I pray you be wise and pray for an vnderstanding hart, and heare me with grace sobernes: you were lately in prison if ten thousands pounds Execution had bene layd vpon you, and a friend of yours of his owne meere compassion payd the money, and did enfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyse you, and for a full recompence hee onely prayeth you but to loue him, and his children, were you not a monster, if you would desloure his daughter? K: The comparison is not alike: G: Shew the difference: K: In this: that by my very inherent corruption I am continually inforced to lust murder, and what not, and cannot preuent it; G: You haue bene in your olde company, and adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated your spirits, and desyled that meekenes, wherein I left you for shew you me, wherein anything is required of you, but if you loue the Lord and giue sound obedyence by continuall labour as you ought, I say tell mee what <hi>Christ Jesus hath left vndone to dissoden you of the whole Lawe, as well for cogitation as and required nothing of you but that you defile nor his Daughter,</hi> his espoused wife, his Temple <hi>and his owne cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen seate in pour hart,</hi> Kni: <hi>But</hi> who can be pure in thought which is the transgressions of the Lawe, and violating all obedyence
<pb facs="tcp:177877:14"/> Gent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uen he that greeueth for the impuritie of his thoughts, and prayeth instantly vnto the Lambe Christ Iesus, to helpe his impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and wash his bespottednesse, and doth what hee can by aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning filthy company, and occasion of sinne, and for his rest taketh hold of him, <hi>Who hath bidden vs cast our burden vpon him, and call vpon him in the daies of trouble, and he will heare:</hi> Psal. 50. 5. and 34. because hee knoweth that our burthen must be made light by him, and our weake saith to apprehend his promises, must <note place="margin">Mat. 11.</note> receiue strength from him: Whereupon it is, that the Apostle calleth our righteousnesse <hi>the righteousnesse of God.</hi> Rom. 2. What can you say my knight, for any impossibility imposed vpon you by the law? K: Smilingly: truly nothing Gentleman: doe you smile? beware of an euill heart, and seeke to weepe for your proud and prophane words, which argue you reuolt from that you were: and I say againe, sorrow that euer sathan should so haue seduced you, as to make you mutine and accuse our sweete Lord, to haue delat pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicially with vs in his most equall statutes K: I pray you good my Gent: conceit mee not vnkindly Gent: What shall I gaine by censuring and grieuing you? for sathan meaneth to weaken mee by your relapse: but let you and I, and all the world, beware how wee dally with the diuell: for if after such a searching, washing, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of our hearts, the Lord hath throwne sathan out, wee reciue <hi>him againe into conference, and forget our continuall claime, no doubt hee will returne with many worse then himselfe,</hi> and cast the Lord quite out of all our holds: and so our ending shall be worse then our begining. K: I pray you sweete Gent: (who hast with such labour and care wrought teares out of mine eyes) haue patience with mee still, and from some part of our former discourse, enlarge <note place="margin">Prisoners cōferenc.</note> something vpon obedience vnto me, I shall thereby more haply be more capable. G: I haue told you alreadie that it is a friend, a companion, nay the mother of meekenesse and patience, because there must be some aduerse opposite occasion, vnto natures aspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, whereby meekenesse euen byobedience to the law resisting, preuaileth: <hi>And so possesseth her soule in patience, which apprehen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat.10.</note>
               <hi>hope, which ministreth assurance, and begetteth watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse
<pb facs="tcp:177877:14"/> and that feare which is blessed</hi> Pro. 23. hence groweth the violence for the kingdome which grownded vpon fayth, the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all, inustereth vs into the very kingdome it selfe: as very sonnes and heyres with Christ Iesus euen as stones be compacted in a building <hi>I goe to my father and your father <hi>Iohn</hi> the</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>K: you speake very well: but teach me from our former confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, me thinks that doth sauour and settle better with me: G: Indeed I would do any thing though you haue wounded me by your care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse questions. K: I pray you forgiue haply I greiue my selfe G I pray you do so: and take for a rule to examine your hart that same demaund of the Lord in the former exercise, <hi>my sonne giue me thy hart.</hi> K. I would giue it but he will not take it G that is because you <note place="margin">Pro. 23.</note> dissemble in your offer, for you would not giue it wholy but by parts, and he will haue alll or none, and now to silence you vtterly, that you may by rebuke, learne to make conscience of your words vnto the great God, speake vnto me in the word of truth how many times your whole wil in words and deeds haue consented vnto vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty since I left &amp; you promised to giue your hart, speak before y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lord: K: Nay good Sir be not so peremptory with me I beseech you G. I peremptory? no farre be it from me: but according to your demaund from the former conference I set a glasse before you to see &amp; finde your spots in your owne face, and not in Gods gloryous face, by this you shall see how farre you haue bene from giuing your hart accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly as you semed willing, and yet you feare not to accule the Lord that he will not take your hart offered vnto him, and lets beware of his greatnes, though his goodnes be infinit and ful of Longanimyty O that some of those poore simple seduced men, who will be called Catholikes, and slander our Church for liberty to sin, did but feele what I feele euen now when I writ this of horror and astonishment &amp; trembling of hart, for disobedience in youth, in age, in ignorance and knowledg? so as indeed I am almost strengthlesse in my appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions for deliuerance and therfore sweet Sir let vs both learn thus to examine our selues: if we be giuen to the vice of the flesh, let vs abandon all secret cogitations of vanity, all company of such as by consent or example, may kindle the sparkes: if drunkards, abandon
<pb facs="tcp:177877:15"/> the company of idle and loose men, who passe their time in tipling and drinking for not only the drunkards, but the drinkars are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the kingdome and if the Lord find vs faythfuly labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thus in the worke of his vincyard, he will so affect vs, as to take our harts whether we will or no <hi>Tales sumus <hi>sayth a father</hi> qualia sunt quotidiana Coloquia &amp;c.</hi> now our obedyence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisting in a posible continuewed violence to giue the Lord our harts what vnequal or vnreasonable things is demaunded? nay what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; in reason more desired happynes, then that the Lord wil abase him selfe to demaund our harts, to mould and knead them anew for his owne delight and table, and as for the same Law where at you so stumble I pray you: and let al men hold this perswasion, that nothing at all is <hi>required but that by prayer, and amanly abandoning sin, may well enough be obtayned</hi> hoth for our fredome from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of sinne, and slauery of sinne: as also for that other more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous end to be engrassed vnto Christ and so vnited into the duty, K. I haue one other doubt shal I bewray it? G. If it please you, K. what needeth the Lord my labour to help him to renew my hart, and change, G: I demaund of you why a Master will try his seruant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he trust him? but I will giue your a reason: he demaundeth your labor because he loueth your obedyence he that laboureth not: must not eate: and because his demaund should make your repudiate and swere a perpetuall diuorce betwixt Sathan, sinne and that hart, which you haue giuen him you must shew your selfe <hi>to encounter the serpent</hi> I tould you of a continuall: clay me alas I am but weake harted my selfe and these your doubts do wound me: for it is not yout sinne, nor you speech that indeed doth perplex me so much, though greue me, as the vnfounlding your wants do speake my particular faylings in my standing, and therefore let vs labour that we may by Gods mercy preuent a totall and finall reuolt. and I hope all the death that euer my spirit shall tast of: for the last <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eperacion that is a sweet passage, and though it may be paineful yet the Lord will assist vnto the ende, and the remembrance of what we striue for will make all things easy and sweet neither do I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne for any thing but for want of conference and counsell to
<pb facs="tcp:177877:15"/> stand fast that I might take delight in the Saints, yet hereein am I letten fall, and wounded past all my strength I am that reproached <hi>Cast away Syon whom no man séekest; after, and euen</hi> abashed to repayre into their companyes, by alienation of their countenan: ces, so am that man subiect vnto Salamons censure, <hi>Woe vnto him that is alone.</hi> K: Well since I see your exceeding loue and care of mee, euen to grow into passion by view of my vnreformed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as a thing peculyar by sence of others smarts that your owne mileryes sease vpon you, giue mee leaue to extend that strength I haue to comfort thee my very sweet companion. G: Will you loue mee so much? Indeede you know not what you giue vnto the Lord by that meanes, therefore I imbrance you and pray the Lore make my harte worthy your counsell, and very deepe kindnesse. K: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst our next meeting, I will desire of God to giue mee a worde of comfort for you. G. I thanke you sweet hart: for indeede I am so much casten away if there were no other cause, <hi>But that I write and professe christianity:</hi> K. I sware it is true: Well I will <note place="margin">Deu. 2.</note> leaue you a little. G: <hi>The Lord rideth vpon the heauens for help of his Church: The eternall God is thy refuge: and vnder his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isaiah. 62.</note>
               <hi>arme thou art sure for euer: He shalleast downe allenemyes and say destroy them.</hi> K How doe you yet my Sir? What reade you? G. An excellent place of Deutronomony and <hi>Isaiah.</hi> K: Shall I know them? G. Yes I pray you reade them. K. it is a strong hold indeede, well, you will giue mee leaue to deale in all loue with you, as you did with mee? G: Yes with all my hart. K: Then I wil proceede with you, as you did with mee, that there may be no loue lost, haue you kept that violence in your selfe, which you ympose vpon me as a matter of such necessitie. G. I thanke you sweete Sir: No the Lord knoweth: for I did thinke all the worst had bene past and ouerweened my selfe, and enlarged my hart vnto foolish presumption, of liberty, chaunge, and what not. So the Lord did euen faithfully strike me in the hart, and I was euen all dead K. But yee did not commit wickednes? G. I know not: for I am sure my hart was very bad, and forgetfull of fromer vowes, and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons did foolishly presse after, desire of liberty. K. But you did not
<pb facs="tcp:177877:16"/> proceede vnto ill transgression? G. I transgressed by conuersing with the vnreformed, and enlarging my hart vnto vanity. K. for the latter iudge your selfe; But for the former it was the Prophet Dauids plight, <hi>Which complayneth he was forced to dwell in the Tents of the vngodly.</hi> G: Indeede my sweet Knight, giue what censure you will, for I am guilty of the transgression of the whole Lawe, both in knowledge, and feeling, and so indeede am euen at faynthing. K: There be foure speciall vses in your estate. First that God will not haue you perish with the carelesse world: Secondly that he will not haue you long out of his fauour by straying abroad: Thirdly that by all your feares hereafter, and astonishments what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer, this is his onely purposes crying alowd vnto your hart, <hi>Come vnto me call vpon me, why wilt thou perish in thy sinnes and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptions.</hi> And thus preuenteth by timely returning that you shall not be famished for want of outward meanes and lastly wee shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the prise of our high calling euen by the open experiences of our sences.</p>
            <p>Therefore for a during rule, let vs haue the Lawe before vs, as a glasse euery day: and be sure to examine and try our harts, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our predominant sinnes how wee haue done that which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and resisted that which is forbidden, So shall wee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare resigned vnto the Mr. of the combat, <hi>Who will giue the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory vnto those that striue lawfully though neuer so weakely.</hi> For Fayth consisteth not in the measure, (but in the affectionate desire this I know is heauy vnto nature, but sweet and easy vnto grace.</p>
            <p>But I pray you Knight, are you willing to conferr with mee in earnest, and purpose to labour for the Kingdome?</p>
            <p>K. Yes in good earnest. G: then let vs informe our selues frō the preuidice of our courses, since that loue of God cannot moue vs, and let vs dwell a little vpon that place of <hi>Peter: <hi>What profit had you then by those thinges whereof you are now ashamed,</hi>
               </hi> let vs examine our owne harts what we haue gayned by sinne? let vs examine the state of others how they haue gayned? and set downe our resolution, and iudgement according to the end? and let vs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the vice of the flesh for the example. K: So wee shall make
<pb facs="tcp:177877:16"/> our selues odious. G: not at al remēber how the incestuous man was receyued and kissed of the whole congregation, after sorrow for his sinne? <hi>Nay see the compassion of the Apostle: that he should not be surprised with sorrow:</hi> I feare me you will still dwell in the flesh <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.</note> pots of Egipt: odious? Let me be accepted with Christ; and a straw for all the phantasticall children of vanity in the world: For if we haue not proclaymed defyance vnto their courts and alyances, al our vowes are in vayne, now for the motyue to vndergoe this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, since our victory is layd vp with Christ Iesus, what should dismay vs? The scorne of the vnreformed? alas, what haue wee to doe with them vnlesse by way of contagyon in their fellowship, the vertue will loue vs, and take pleasure in our communitis, reade our exercises, and fight with vs, in the spirit for holynes and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence as the Apostle speaketh: and wee our selues by our willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and Gods blessing, <hi>Shall forget and smile at the shame that some foolish shame, which appeareth in our changed estates, <hi>Isaiah 54.</hi> wherein our very beauty is changed by our correction:</hi> This shall be forgotten I say, and in account prised, a high seruice vnto the Lord, &amp; we shall haply inioy our beauty agayne, as those which beeing deluiered from feare, serue the Lord, <hi>in holynes and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes all the dayes of our liues:</hi> O that wee had vnderstanding harts, and stable parts in vs; I make no question: but you and I doe know some men so horribly confounded in wheredome, as hauing great liuings they consume all vpon filthynes and passe their time at playes, that same prophane exercise which robbeth the poore, <hi>and indéed is the Semyuary of al vncleane and filthy matches: a</hi> reuerend father in detestation thereof (Tertulion I take (it writeth thus. <hi>Nihill est nobis, nisu auditu, vel dictu: cum iuspudicita hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trae.</hi> But wee will returne I haue wronged you sweet hart: but you, will pardon I would remoue what euer should binder our very o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and plaine tendred obedyence vnto the Lord, and must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse vnto you, that in seeking to strengthen you, I am very weak and casten downe my selfe, for no small or ordinary tempests, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company my hart euen to disable, and cast me downe quite out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, refused, scorned, contemned; euen of those who before they
<pb facs="tcp:177877:17"/> knew me truely honoured me, and now they see that the Lord hath drawne me through this red sea of lingering attendance, <hi>depsise me, and dispute my ende;</hi> alas poore weake men: For the Lord doth know how desirous I am to doe euery man right, and griue euen deepely that I haue not any thinges, eyther to sell or pawne to pay them: that the creartions of God in my hart might rest without their mutining censures, but herein is my death, as that same designed quarter for tryall of obedyence.</p>
            <p>G. then thus: we in our prodominant sinnes pride, excesse Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very or whosoeuer, haue continued not only the time of our youth, but euen of ourage; of ignorance and knowledg in them a high measure of prouocatiō then affliction that happy visiter and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer he seizeth vpon vs, and we cry vnto God, and if he should deliuer vs presently we should gayne as little as <hi>Pharoah <hi>by</hi> Moses <hi>rod but y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cole was put vnto his lips, by the sling Angel y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> he should not hastyly forget the message wherevnto he was designed: and</hi>
               </hi> why should not wee suffer the time of our curing, according vnto the wilful sway of our carlesse wandering? and pray se the Lord that hathnot consumed vs, in our guilt, So it is proportinable that wee do endure a heauy distracting age, for a long mispent youth: excesse is to be cured by want: the vice of the flesh by diseases feares, and pouerty: why do I dispise the portion and medicine? if I know my selfe wounded by guilt and so of therest must I be straight discharged as sone as I cry for smart then shall I gayne playne nothing: why were the Isralites, excercised 40. <hi>yéeres in the Wildernes, but to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate &amp; poūd</hi> y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> perpetual, acknowledgment of their mighty wroght liberty and enfranchment out of so strang a captiuity being <hi>the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry birth and propagtion of the Church:</hi> therefore wee see the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary course of goods sauing prudence in the depth of his loue, to afflict vs euen to the same end, not otherwise then as need requireth 1 Pet. 16. what haue we to do with lymmiting of times? but let the Lord alone were it not a strange speech a wounded man should say to his surgeon: <hi>This is enough, &amp; thus long wil serue: No, no</hi> we may not so proceed, nether must we be weary, but walk in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> image of our redeemer, in patience, obedience, &amp; meeknes, <hi>we haue not yet
<pb facs="tcp:177877:17"/> resisted vnto blood: we must work our our saluation in feare, &amp; so fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish our course with ioy.</hi> Since the Lord is God, &amp; pittieth the state <note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> of our mortalitie, why are we dismayd? and why feare we? sithence al the world feareth him that defendeth vs, as we haue had experience this many yeres, you are not vsually so dull and dead, how chanceth it? what is the reason? K: Nothing but all well. G: Well, will you stir vp your selfe and I will report a strange storie of a distres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed man, as you haue heard, whose peace, happinesse, and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reward was such, after many fearefull endured tempestes, as would make all easie and sweete vnto you and me, in our more easie conditions. K: I pray you quicken mee with it. Ge: Then I partly say vnto you an afflicted man, who hauing passed of long a red sea of tempests and stormes, it pleased God to touch him in his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in his wife, and in himselfe: the mother fell into despaire, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into the passion of the heart, continuall watch and care was had to dispossesse them of all the liuing they had, if the were absent, this man in this wofull perplexity, must of necessity repaire to London, he must carry his wife with him, hee must leaue his liuing and his children euen to the deuourers; the Lord said vnto him, <hi>Get thée out of thy fathers house, and hee did goe:</hi> he had neither money nor meanes, but by selling of that which should haue beene the stay of his children. hee had a hundred pound to pay at London at tymes alreadie past, his wise with childe, he in continuall danger of arrest, and to be taken from her: was not this a heauy plight my knight? K: Yes the Lord knoweth: I Pray you what was the end? Gent: Gratious and good, though heauie and fearefull for the time: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the iourney to London, newes doth meete him, like that of Iob, that his aduersaries in law, are continually at the Exchequer bar, and if hee doe not make present appearance with his counsell, both his cause and credite were vtterly ouerthrowne. This cause could not be maintained but by money; alas he had none, nor peace, nor hope in his estate, neither was lie able to deuise any remedie: all men see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to wonder at his extreamities, and were wearie to heare report of them; the heauens denied to smile vpon him, and the earth had cast him out, his children at home in danger to be swallowed vp and
<pb facs="tcp:177877:18"/> case out of all: well in this wofull plight, without any hope in the world but as a man carryed by officers to receieiued ment in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistary of cruelty, (or such was his feeling) he came vp to Lond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, neuer man in such misery for feare of arre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, (which he continually expected,) as fearing therby the vtter ouerthrow of his wife and cast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away of her child, in this perplexity bee repayred to his credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to whom this hundred was due. The creditor seeing the state of <note place="margin">D. P.</note> the man wounded, both in body and mind did wonderfully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him, and rayse him vp to apprehend the promises of God, and not only with wordes but preuenting him that he should not grieue for fayling day with him, did giue him longer day wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lingly, which hee did not onely performe, but (digest well what I write Knight, nay let all the world digest it) for a thing memorable both in God, and the party: This Creditor vnderstanding of the great charges of the poore Gentleman in the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ty, and that his causes in Lawe were presently to bee managed, did demaund of him what store of money hee had? at which very wordes the Gentlemans hart did breake and hee did fall into passion, which he seeing spoke thus. Nay: beleeue me sayth he, we wil not haue mony matters make vs so sorrowfull, <hi>and so to conclude did lend the Gentleman three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score pound more vpon his owne hand:</hi> Whereby hee recouered <note place="margin">A rare Creditor.</note> strength to himselfe, comfort to his wife, and ouerthrow vnto all his aduersaryes in Lawe: what say you my Knight, haue I not stird you vp with a story K: Yes wonderfully I sweare vnto you. G: Then take for conclusion as great a wonder as this. The Mr of the house where the Gent: and his wife lay, at the red Bull without Newgate, (beeing about to depart, hauing payde all, demaunded of the Gent: what store of mony he had, the Gentleman answered hee had not much, but that hee thought would bring him home in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his country: The Mr. answered, well Sir I haue no great store of mony to lend you, but such as I haue, take with you to borrow mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of if you need, <hi>And so deliuered him 3 fayre gilt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iuer bowles in a case to be caryed at the saddle how, and willed him pay for them at the yeares ende 26 pound.</hi> Lo my worthy Knight how all these fearefull tempestes did sort into a sunne-shine calme of happy
<pb facs="tcp:177877:18"/> deliuerance, loe Sir what cause haue wee to sorrow that wee should forget thankfulnes to this Lord whose eyes tend vpon the afflicted, for you know we concluded that when the Lord would make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant diuorece betwixt vs, the word and Sathan at once, <hi>we should finde all Sathans practises inflamed against vs,</hi> as they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this man in example: <hi>And what gayned Sathan,</hi> though the man for the time was strengthlesse? Yet God did see that for his owne glory hee made him, <hi>without power to helpe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,</hi> and therefore he did manage all his matters, and gaue him Conquest, <hi>Euen Sathan vanquished?</hi> did ye neuer reade nor heare Sir, the story of a reuerend man who hauing beene long afflicted, and after finding some rest did grow wonderfull heauy harted, and a friend of his comming to him, fel into a bitter weeping taking vp the cōplaints of Syon the 49. of I <hi>sayah <hi>that God had forgotten him, and his Lord had forsaken him?</hi>
               </hi> I assure you my Knight, I haue beene some yeares together in the trembling of the hart, and it hath ceased, and I haue feared more then before, an when it hath come agayne I haue embraced it though no creature so bad and baren for making vse as my selfe: it is my sinne, &amp; I desire others to make better profit of misteries of our deare God: &amp; beseech him, the world may learne by the example of my long continued affliction, not to dally with Sathan, <hi>in a seruice of so neare required attendance, as I haue much abused:</hi> the Lord euen Iesus forgiue me, for I am so broken &amp; abandomed comunitie of the godly, thrown out into the places of dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, that I haue much adoe to preuent euen grose euils: it shallbe better when the Lord wil. In the meane time let vs returne &amp; deeply stir vp one another, in this sweet and most righly required, obedy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: K: I pray you make Away Gent: G: Looke ye Sir if a Lord of a mannor bee confined nere an vsurping neighbour who pretendeth title vnto his Lordsship, and for his owne defence the Lawe presscri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth that continuall clayme be made for continuance of his right, if you be put in trust to make this claime and sayle therein, are you not criminally guilty beeing made acquainted before what waight the matter was of. K: Yes in good earnest. G Why then thus my sweet hart: The Lord by the redemption of the gentle Iesus hath chose for himselfe your hart, and my hart, to haue I say a peculyar
<pb facs="tcp:177877:19"/> mansion for himselfe, and this continuall claime bee made for the Lambes right, now from the beginning Sathan will haue enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the sauiour, <hi>For it was so decrée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to engage the Children of</hi> the couenant, that for exercise of their continuall clayme for the <note place="margin">Gen. 6.</note> gentle Mr. the should stand in the gappe against the intruding Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than and make continuall clayme, this is the matter required of vs, this is the price demaunded euen for our whole, and perpetual salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that our harts soules &amp; spirits strength be prepared in defyance of Sathan, to defend our Mr. his possessions, and specially since hee hath pleased to make our euill harts a mansion and pallace for his sacred residence. K: But I pray you doe you this duety your selfe?</p>
            <p>G: Alas I haue told you that I am woe, that I haue not and do it not, why will you still looke vpon me, who am ten thousand times behind all men? the question is not who doth this duty? but what degree of faythfull obedyence euery man ought by labour &amp; watch fulnes to aspyre vnto, for glory of his owne Creator, Redeemer, and Redemption? and to seale vp the certainty thereof in carying the Lordes image and discarding the world, it is the continued enmity in our owne bowels, against our strong naturall man, that offereth the acceptable obedyence, and violence for the Lambes Robe: Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse and Kingdome which shall inuest vs into the assurance of fayth and possession of our soules, <hi>In this quiet fruit of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes</hi> which is called our rest. KI pray you Sir what is obedience.</p>
            <p>Gent: Obedience I take to be a harborough of a working hand <note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> of Gods spirit by regenerating grace: Apprehended soundly by Faith: Established by hope: Continewed by loue: Distributed by violence, out of an industruous commanding rule ouer the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of sinne: Pressing after the Author and finisher of our Fayth. Heb: 12: Thus I conceaue by reason of the continuall apposition betwixt nature and grace: For grace respecteth the Masters demaund of our whole hart, soule and strength: and nature dwelleth below opposing against this holy preparation, and pleadeth for the world and momentary vanities: but in a worde for the knowledge of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyence digest the whole Lawe and euery perticular branch thereof in your hart, and where you finde disobedience the contrary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb facs="tcp:177877:19"/> is obedience and I wil giue you a fine rule from the word euen the 30. of <hi>Isaiah</hi> which shalbe your light, and your staffe: euen the spirit of truth <hi>In all the alterations of your life, shall by an effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall worde sound in your eares, this is the right way go it: that is the wrong way auoyde it.</hi> This is the heauenly permonishing grace of God, who both sheweth vs what is harmefull in our wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to auoyde it, and of it selfe helpeth vs to passe by offensiue pits, and remoue the snares: God neuer requireth any thing of man, but hee knoweth that man hath neither will nor deede of himselfe to any performance, and therfore doth attend, and as it were, <hi>hold the torch himselfe to take view of our beginning, &amp; endeuors for obedience and he himselfe will worke it out for a most certaine, and sweet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.5.</note>
               <hi>seruice vnto him,</hi> and thus wee fulfill the whole Lawe of God: <hi>Opera dei sunt peccata tua sunt et cum premium venerit sua dona non tua merka coronabit</hi> K: I am weary I can tell you G: So am I, I assure you a little, but let vs recreate our selues with a question you shall pose me if you will, or I you. K. What is the question? G. It is this because wee haue spoken much of patience and meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes before: Let vs now enquire how obedyence is allyed, or rather knit in line of blood with meekenes and patience, and whether it bee a Mother or a Sister. K: a Mother it cannot bee. G: Why? K: Because they bee the gifts of God. G: That is nothing: shall wee say that loue is not an effect of the spirit, because the spirit is the gift of God? and shall wee say that prayer is not the infant of Faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause Faith is the gift of God. K: Indeede I am sad and dead har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: G: Nay it may not be so, for wee conferre to praise God; sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes groweth euer from corruption or from censure thereof, when it is priuate, therefore let mee not haue you sad, for when you were not so strong as now, by the grace of God you neuer discouraged mee thus: But I remember when I was a boy sent for from schoole vnto my fathers house, if I stayed a weeke there, I should be more vntoward a moneth after: So I feare mee you haue wronged your selfe by abusing your liberty. K: Indeede you doe touch my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry right, and in respect thereof I am sad at the hart. G. Well: accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the truth of your sad hart in compunction of any thing mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done,
<pb facs="tcp:177877:20"/> the Lord is exorable: and I pray grieue me no more then is fit, for I am not so strong as I haue beene: stire vp therefore your selfe, and let vs speak <hi>of this kindred (as I may say) betwixt obedience, méekenesse, and patience.</hi> K: In leede I am not able. G: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I: but let vs shew what we thinke (weakely as is) and the godly learned will helpe vs. K: Good sir, I cannot; neither can you I thinke. G: I thanke you for that motiue, to make me delue deepe into all my faculties; and I say <hi>Obedience is the mother,</hi> and I <note place="margin">Obediēce Mother.</note> proue it thus: there is neither knowne meekenesse nor patience, but in regard of some resisting violence offered vnto nautre or grace, or them both: but Obedience is the common mother which giueth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample both to work Resistance, and to endure wrongs (<hi>for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement sake</hi>) therefore from obedience, as from a common Ancestor issueth both meekenes and patience: for hos is it known who is meeke and patient before some tentations haue made try all of their Obedyence? Then the mother that hathlearned to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure all for her welbeloued, <hi>shee paryfieth her Childrens, méeknesse and patience, and biddeth them bée still</hi> I leaue it to the learned: onely this I conceaue as yet so obedyence is al <hi>you are my friends saith the Lamb if you keepe my commaundements</hi> which is onely and solely by obedience, for as tribulation tryeth obedience so imediatly obedience, bringeth forth patience, K: <hi>Nay the place that you</hi> alledged as: <hi>you are my friends if you loue one</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohu. 14. 15.</note>
               <hi>another</hi> G: well we wilnot contend for the matter you are somthing waspish and deceiued herein at this time: but shew you the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: betwixt obedience and loue indeed it will eyther quicken you, or astonish you the more, K. nothing at all: we may loue one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and be far from obedyence G: that is the thing in question and imposible since loue is commaunded answre Knight. K. I proue that loue is only in outward things and the Profit sayth <hi>my goods extend not vnto thee but to the Saynts below,</hi> so we may loue our neighbour for al we haue outwardly and yet be disobedient, G: Alas <note place="margin">Psal. 16.</note> how weakly? hath not y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lord command our goods because he hath on need of them? it is high time we should meet againe for the first branch of the commaund is to loue the Lord our God withall our
<pb facs="tcp:177877:20"/> hart soule &amp; strength &amp;c. wherein is contayned that by force of this loue we must seeke for the knowledg of our God for <hi>Taniuus d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naus quantum credimus.</hi> K. Very good: G. And do I oue my selfe no more but for my outward goods to eated inke sleepe, and come in when it rayneth? and haue I no care to the word and to keepe the Saboth, and to aueyd open impietyes? if I haue this loue and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg for God in my selfe? I am bound to labour as well to inuest my bretheren thereinto, <hi>and this is the second table wherein the first is established as in linke breake one and breake all,</hi> so the truth is, that I must shew the oue that I owe vnto God by drawing my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to the obedience of his law, and this is a whole and sound obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyence for the members cannot be separated from the head neyther one from another so it is a high degree of obedyence that we labor to inuest others into the same knowledg of true obedyence vnto the whole law of God, with vs as well, as giue them a peice of bread, or a nights lodging K. But who digesteth or practiseth this? G. I pray you let me not find you thus peruers what is the rason man? because you are come to schoole agayne? what if no liuing man do it. Is it not therfore the cōmandemēt of God: K. in good earnest y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lord be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyful vnto me, the hearing of obedyence &amp; that must quiteabādon all vnreformed company, though I knew enough beforeyer did sur prise me, but Y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lord be mercyful vnto me I say &amp; wil by his strēgth arise, &amp; I pray you my Gen: help me with your desires indeed I wil: but truely the only peace of all desires and quiet rest in spirit is from this same obedyence, which Sathan maligneth, that we should agree in: <hi>But the Lord shall bruise his head, and giue vs peace,</hi> and therefore doe you tell me sir, from that experience you haue of God and from those teares which dropped grace vnto your heart, what is your owne secret conceit of this obedience? K: I must tell you it is a most heauie ymposition vnto mee, considering what I feele. G: Haply as heauie vnto mee: <hi>but this must quicken vs to more carefull labour, and not discourage vs: let God be true, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and holy, and all men lyars.</hi> K: But I pray you can you giue obedience to the law? G: Yes that I can. K: Then you shall liue by the law. G: So I will <hi>For</hi> Christ <hi>came to fulfill the law:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:177877:21"/> Christ <hi>is your stabilitie of the law, and euen he the slaine Lambe, is giuen vnto me with all his holinesse and righteousnesse:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the Apostle concludeth; <hi>That the righteousnesse of the law is fulfilled in vs by him.</hi> Rom. 3. 4. K: And yet yo say you are a heynous transgressor of the whole law G: SO I am truly: but my humble and harty acknowledgement of my transgressions, is my strength, and taking hold of my saith, carrieth me vnto him, who hath fully both satisfied, and cancelled the law: <hi>For he came to saue sinners.</hi> K. May euery man hold this assurance? G: Yes if hee haue the same faith. K: You answer me with if. G: Good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that I deale plainelywith you: for Christ came to saue beleeuers, and if any man beleeue not <hi>he is none of</hi> Christs: <hi>but he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeueth is passed from death.</hi> Whither? <hi>Surely into life: neither into Purgatorie nor fléepe</hi> which since the Lord setteth before mee to enquire of, stir vp your selfe in Gods name, and bee enlarged for my reliefe, as you haue beene (sweete harte.) Gent. Any thing in the world that I can, as willingly as I breath. K: tell me then your opinion touching dispayre, something by the way you did touch it in the former prisoners Conference: But I would heare you at large. G. Alas this is the most vnfit season that euer could be: being so weake my selfe and yet I receiue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, by the wordes of a reuerend man (remembred vnto mee by a true euer louing brother) who hauing purposed to comment vpon <hi>Iob,</hi> presently fell sicke and so continewed all the time of his labour therein, and did confesse that the Lord was a wonderfull helper vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him by the very meanes of his sicknes, as he sayed <hi>vt compressis Iob compressus exponerem et vulnerati mentem per verbara sentenam:</hi> that hee was made more fit by the feeling of afflictions, how to iudge softly, and soberly, of the afflicted; right so I must assure you that my estate hath beene wonderfully shaken, with many degrees of my weakenes in temptation euen lately, and many horrors threaten mee euen now round about, both in minde, and body, but I will desire the Lord to be mercifull vnto mee, that out of my owne pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate sence and feeling of so heauy a plight, I may speake somthing vnto you of his righteous compassion, in my owne expereicnes
<pb facs="tcp:177877:21"/> which may bee ayding to my selfe and others but specially your good selfe, if neede require. But alas if my feeling be taken away, where is my apprehension of strength for others? and of this feeling hath no man assurance but at will only: for if otherwise: the strong would deuoure the weake: but the sence of death, and terrour of afflictions: and that men bee subiect vnto the same misery, doth so apaule the deuouring oppressors, that euen biting, they stay their humors, and deuouring conceits, <hi>wounding is the mighty simplicitie of Truth:</hi> Let no man ouerweene himselfe sayth the Apostle, <hi>But he who séemeth to stand let him beware he fall not: you who are strong saith ho</hi> Gala: 6. <hi>restore and comfort the weake with softnes, not pleasing your selues, considering you may be circumuented by Sathan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is one place which I confesse vnto you doth threaten and wound me, K. Why what place should wound you, that in all the changes of your afflictions haue found in the same worde a a sauing and soueraigne medicine? G. you say well: it should bee otherwise, but herein you must haue a wise hart and handle a bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>spirit with tender hands, &amp; soft spéeches for truely the gréene wound will quickly bléed:</hi> For as the worde is omnesufficient <note place="margin">Hosea 5.</note> for this life, and that to come, yet all flesh must know that it is but grasse, and must fade as the flower at the rebuke of the Lord, the fyer will consume the drosse: and fyne the Gold and will burne so long as it findeth matter to be burned: So the pretious loue of our deare God will continew his afflictions <hi>So long as he findeth so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluity of iniquitie in our mortalitie, as that same purging and medcinable fire.</hi> K. I hope you account not your selfe drosse? G. Not altogether: Nor finally I hope: but my weakenes may wound the Church in many particulars, from the Truth I haue written vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others if I fall my selfe. Where learne you to feare your fall, G. Euen from the Apostles words before alledged and the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of my weakenes: <hi>My pride and arrogancy hath deceiued me, and my foolish boldnes hath brought me into desolate wayes.</hi> K: Well you are sory for it, and ioy not in it, neyther wish it should liue in you, and therefore returne vnto the place of <hi>Osey.</hi> G. Alas
<pb facs="tcp:177877:22"/> you know I was bolde to conclude comfortably from thence vnto the wounded patient, euen so farre as his vntowardnes should not driue away the mercyfull Phisition though hee sayd hewould bee gone, and now mee thinkes he sayth to mee hee will depart and bee like a I you vnto me which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ugh I know he came be yet in absēce? sathan may deuoure mee Then is God vntrue: Who hath bound himselfe both by his word and <hi>oath to deliuer vs from Sathan: and therevpon hat inioyned a request peculiarly for that:</hi> And <note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note> fie that you fall into such sencelesse absurdities, since you haue strenghned mee with a word of assurance, <hi>if the mother could for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get her child yet cannot I forget thée sayth the Lord. <hi>Esay:</hi>
               </hi> 49. ver. 15. <hi>what can Sathan do than.</hi> G. Sathan can do enough against an vnbeleeuer. K. Who is an vnbeleeuer? G. Hee which cannot take hold of Gods promises. K. I say you blaspheame: <hi>Haue you not said no man hath like beléefe and feeling at all times? haue you not concluded that the desire to beléeue is sufficient? and to mourno because you cannot beleeue is a sauing Fayth?</hi> I will bee <note place="margin">Perkins.</note> gone if you thus pull downe your former building. G. Well I lie not for I haue beene since I see you, that I had neyther firme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, nor sound hope, neyther durst well pray by reason of the guilt of my hart. K: What then you grieued in that state did yee not? G. Yes so as was. K: Wel you may do wel <hi>to speake good of the Lord,</hi> and not make euery temptation a downefall, <hi>but be strong and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise in the saluation of God,</hi> I could speake something bitterly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you but will not. G, Now I beseech you in all our loue doe so: for no man will help mee to ransacke my euill hart. K: Indeede I will not: It was but a conceit of weakenes: I know you haue indured too much for me to prize or censure, yet the Lord hath bin your strength, and that is a crowne vpon your head: and a bar in the enemyes mouthes, and let them still practise (if the will of God be so) and be not you weary of wel doing, <hi>but be sure when men doe band against you, the Lord meaneth to giue glory vnto you.</hi> G. I must needes confesse that your extreamities, and my owne wants haue wounded mee very much, and after many yeares hpe in my perticuler suite, to bee still preuented by oppression, and practise, to leaue mee in the streets for want of meanes to defend my selfe,
<pb facs="tcp:177877:22"/> doth greatly shake mee, for feare to wound the cause of my reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. K: But why doubt you. G: Because I sinne daily. K: How doe you sinne? G: In cogitations and vnprofitable thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of desired libertie. Doe you take pleasure therein? G: I thinke I doe not: I am sure I would not. K: Why then march on though you fall, arise, and pray helpe of others G: No man will helpe me, but all men forsake and dispute me: K: But the Lord doth not, neither euer will, do you hope so? G: Yes indeede weakely; and the rather because he hath brought my desires so low, as to liue in any seruice or calling in the world, where I might with labour and paines get any thing to pay my debts, I would neuer aske more; but euen leaue my children, my sighs and teares for portion, though my hope was much by my late sacred Mistris <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> K: Be you not then out of heart, since your Lo: hath conformed you vnto the obedience of his Sonne, to forget and forsake all to follow him? G: Yes truly, in some weake sort I doe feele it. K: Well, will you reioyce and tell me your opinion of despaire. G: Truly it is a thing much spoken of, and is grieuous for the present, but worketh wonderfully and changeth water into Wine. K. What doe you thinke of it. G. I feare it: and I feare it not: I feare it in suspition of mine owne weaknes: I feare it not by doubting the ende, which I haue in diuers knowne most blessed vnto the afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. K but in your former discourse you alledged that stuborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in man should make the Lord depart: what stubornnes hath there beene in you towardes Gods will? G. I know not what you call it: but I haue done things forbidden, and left vndone godly thinges commanded. K. Who hath not so done? G. I know not.</p>
            <p>K But haue you had a malicious stuborne spirit of indignitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Lord in your sinning, you speake of stubornnes who was euer so stubborne and openly shut vp in blasphemous wilfull contempt, as <hi>Ionah</hi> about <hi>a trifling delight of his affections, and what renege did the Lord take of this: but by gentle smyling rebuke, doest thou well to be angry? and he answered gracelefly and blasphemously, I dye well to be angry to the death:</hi> Did not the Lord passe by this grieuous contempt, and contumelie? so pray
<pb facs="tcp:177877:23"/> you be comforted for as the Lords patience is not euer to bee assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: No more is his departing to bee limitted, but referred to his gratious pleasure: and therefore I pray you giue mee some better satisfaction why yee said you feared dispayre: and feared it not. G. I say I feare it as a naturall man: and I feare it not as a regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man: I feare it because my sinnes be many and festred, which may make my patience and attendance more distressed to endure the Lordes returne: I feare it neyther in respect of the affliction, <hi>for I know it sanctifieth to the Saints:</hi> Neyther anyotherwise: but least my vnpure poluted parts, should make me breath out any least discontent by blasphemous word or thought, I know the Lord will consume the drosse of my carnall man, that way or some other as it please his gratious maiestie.</p>
            <p>I haue beene present with diuers in this affliction, but they were gentle, righteous, sweet soft harted ones, but I am growne old in my sinns and without the Lords great mercy, <hi>they shall lys downe in the doust with me:</hi> for I haue glutted my selfe in feeding my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, <note place="margin">Iob. 10.</note> and put of sence of the euil day, and in my afflictions haue sought pleasure, and vaine delight <hi>therefore sayth the Prophet I must ly downe in sorrow,</hi> but if I had <hi>sought the saluation of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isaiah. 50. 16.</note>
               <hi>then should I haue called vpon him and he would</hi> answere. <hi>I will heare thée sayth the Lord thy strength, and strong defence,</hi> K. how may this affliction be preuented? G. There is no way to preuent Gods decreed ordinances: yet since we haue learned that this and all other afflictions are but only means to resine our harts vnto y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Lord: indeed the nearest meane to moue him for sparing herein <hi>is to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour our harts euen to imbrace this, or that, or what other tryal or</hi>
               <note place="margin">The vse of affections.</note>
               <hi>discharg fouet it may please him to inioyne</hi> which if wee feare it not by way of heady perswaysion and presumption but in sobernes and ready obedience, <hi>desirous to be crusisied to the world and the world to vs to follow <hi>Christ</hi>
               </hi> and this as a counsell for our resigned preparation for if he will bring glory to his name, and a spoyle vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Sathan by sequestring me for the Lambs garment, in this morta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyty with feare: or dispayre in his Scowring house? why should I scorne the scowrng, <hi>since I would be set vpon the celestial shelfe?</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:177877:23"/> I was present with a reuerent man when a question was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded <note place="margin">(Grene ham)</note> of him by a young Gentleman in distraction, why the Lord should deny the request of a man craueing nothing, but such a lawfull yssue of his attempts, as that he might be knowne to be an honest man in the world? the reuerent father seeing the Gentleman far from meekenes, and full of humors did answere him smartly by way of demaund: why he should tinke to preuayle with God more then Christ and all the Apostles who were vertuous &amp; Godly in al their courses yet could not haue the reputation of tollerable and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest men: so your place is to follow their example by vertue and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrety of life and if you cannot preuaile with the world, <hi>you shall mourne for righteousnes vnto God as they did and be blessed</hi> K. <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 1 Pet. 4. 14.</note> well now I like you, you speake with some life and feeling quickned estate and I pray you discourse vnto me a little what counsell you will giue to the afflicted in heauy plight of dispayre? G. Indeede I haue had experience of this and of other almost as great, and that is where a man is so wounded with outward greefes and paine as he cannot feele the promises, though hee doth beleeue, and desire to feele. K. Then there is no difference at all G. O yes great: for as Salamon saith: <hi>All onlward extremities may be supported by the inward feelings, of hope in a sound spirit:</hi> So this dispayre woundeth the spirit and dispolyeth the facultyes thereof: The other doth not so: but for the time of outward torment only, in respect of sence: but for my counsell in the one and the other this it is: First that the afflicted man doe bring his conscience vnto the Lawe and there simply lay downe his guilt before God, for his faylinges to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes him: and all men without delay, and seeke reconcilement with men: and make restitution if hee haue wronged any eyther in goods or name: Deny no acknowledgement, publike or priuate, according to the quality or the offence? neuer stand vpon feare: or shame, or reproach or whatsoeuer scrupple; <hi>but as he priseth the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Counsel for men in dispaire.</note>
               <hi>returne of God and his faour more then all the world beside, so in the way of his sorrow of sinne, he will abandon the world for his obedience,</hi> thus letting the Lord see that hee will quite abandon all thinges, for his gratious fauour, sorrowing that hee can be no more
<pb facs="tcp:177877:24"/> sory, nor no more contrite, <hi>yet he will vow a seperation of all va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, for his returne</hi> and purpose more vpright watch, and feare in his way, then euer hee did: <hi>and so concludeth I will séeke thy thy face O Lord,</hi> and willingly imbrace to liue in this misery so long as thou in thy compassion shalt thinke fit, I dare giue this word of <note place="margin">Psal. 27.</note> counsell for I know it is the word of Truth, and haue seene the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable effects that followed, a minde thus prepared, both for ease and strength: and for my owne particular, indeede my experience hath beene comfortable with diuers in dispayre, but alas it was in the vnreformed times of my life: but the Lord seeing it would settle no better with me, &amp; least I should be guilty of so great and gratious a call, he did giue leaue to Sathan <hi>to touch me in my life, state, wife, children, causes abroad, dispcylings at home:</hi> So inflicted vpon me a generall astonishment, closing me vp in darkenes, and with poore seduced Saul I was driuen in my gardē to beat my face look vp &amp; say, doubting <hi>Who art thou Lord?</hi> K. I pray you proceede. G. Indeede <note place="margin">Act. 9.</note> it is pertinent to engage obedience in you, my selfe and others, for thervpon was layd before my face, the open view and foulnes of my Leprosie, wherein I walked which is a chiefe matter to bee found in all afflictions: <hi>But it is a more hony swéet thing to try our selues before, then in the time of affliction, for in tentation sethan hath got the start, and will make heauy, and full of impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibilities our best and most required offices:</hi> Yet vnto the poore wounded soule let mee speake the worde of Truth, if thou finde the grace to try and finde thy guilt, or freelest and disobedience, and euen dost mourne, and art vnrested for the burthen thereof: I say <hi>let thy labour and strife goe together with thy sighes vnto God, that the will please to shew thée his way, that thou may walke in it, I say in the truth of Jesus, I dare be thy warraut, march and hope wel:</hi> K: I pray you what assurance haue you of this mercy by any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of those that haue beene afflicted. G. Yes such a sweet hart haue I beene in company of, that in the midst of hells as hee felt, by a generall priuation of all apprehensions of God, sodenly sitting at table amongst vs (after that hee had put mee from him) offering to
<pb facs="tcp:177877:24"/> imbrace him and said hee was Sathan, he stood vp and his eyes loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto heauen, cryed out these wordes: <hi>Now I beséech the Lord let me wéepe one teare:</hi> I sitting by: said: my brother you said you were Sathan, <hi>from whence commeth these greanes to wéepe?</hi> he answered I cannot tell: do yee thinke (said I) that Sathan hath any such compunction as to desire to weepe, that his hart might be soft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? hee answered I thinke as you thinke, though I feele no diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie, <hi>betwixt Sathan and mée:</hi> well said I desire you of God that you may hold that you haue? <hi>I can neyther receiue nor hold saith</hi>
               <note place="margin">The state of a despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate man.</note>
               <hi>he, nor pray for any good thing the wordes that he spoke</hi> hee said were spoken onely out of anguish and guilt with Iudas that speech I tolde him was a very bad speech, and deserued rebuke: his plight was this: <hi>me slept little: e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te nothing, tooke no rest, but walked agast, and frightes vp and downe a parlour all the night: and all the day: be liued for the most part 3. yeares in this plight</hi>
               <note place="margin">his plight</note>
               <hi>withsome gratious intermissions: for his person</hi> as sweet, pure a youngman, in heart I thinke as euer liued: h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s horrors made him <note place="margin">His per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</note> looke fearefully: though hee was wonderfully well fauoured: <hi>Hee durst not come in the Church nor heare the preacher,</hi> but I pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish and testifie to Gods euerlasting praise, that hee receuered both <note place="margin">Maples.</note> grace, and strength, and liued some 4. yeares after to shew loue and thankfulnes, &amp; dyed as sweet a creature as liued (I say I think so) as innocent a man. Therefore the Lord doth not euer afflict for sin: but to giue grace to some, and to fill vp the measure of iniquity to other oppressors: K. I pray you sir report your conferences with him. G. They are too long I feare: but if you require it, I must pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish it because it tendeth directly to Gods glory &amp; may do good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to some others. K. I do know it, and therefore I beseech you do it. G. I demaunded many things of him as whether he did loue God? or whether he desired to do any thing y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> should openly offend God? &amp; he would answere he could not tell: <hi>For hedid neythr loue nor hate.</hi> Then being priuate together: I desired him giue me leaue to loue him: he answered <hi>why should you loue me?</hi> I replyed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I see Christ crucified in your face: <hi>And féele him in your spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> you are deceaued in both (said hee) will yee answere mee one
<pb facs="tcp:177877:25"/> question said I? Hee answered he could not tell: I pray giue your opinion said: I in what plight was Christ, <hi>When he cryed my God my God why hast thou forsaken mee?</hi> And where in is there condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion now worse then his was then? hee was the sonne of God (said hee) <hi>And could not fall away as I haue done:</hi> I answered hee was the sonne of God by nature, and you by adoption and grace. There is the question (said he) <hi>on my part:</hi> I pray you my Brother (said I) tell mee one thing haue you committed any grosse enormious sinne in all your life, that may thus presse and wound your consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? Hee answered yes: <hi>For he had forsaken his first loue:</hi> what is that said I? A lawfull calling to haue gone to Cambridge, but I had more minde to stay in the country and so despised my calling: I replyed what holines or seruice to God, had been in your going to Cambridge? rather then to stay in the country with your father, and instruct him who is thought weake in Religion, and vnrefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in many thinges? what calling haue I vnto that sayd he? yes said I, he that hath commaunded you to honor your father hath impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed vpon you the care of his soule as much as of his body and herein you must depriue your selfe, of a worldly caling to Cambridg to further your fathers saluation or els you haue no true duty and <note place="margin">Bradford.</note> loue: But I pray you what calling had you to Cambridge? euen that calling (sayd he) that if I had gone I had preuented this: alas poore soule (sayd I) do you thinke that you can procure or preuent the Lord in his ordinances of afflictions? I confesse you prouoke the Lord to afflict you: <hi>But in this or any other perticular affliction. You cannot:</hi> There is a deeper matter (said he) in my hart: I beesech you (said I) loue me so much, as let me know it: well if you wil know it said he <hi>I haue lost the Spirit:</hi> I answered you cannot: but I am sure I haue lost (sayd he:) then you neuer had it (sayd I) yes truly (sayd he) that is impossible (sayd I) <hi>for whom the Lord loueth, he loueth to the end:</hi> &amp; how answere you the gradation of the Apostle Rom. 8. <hi>whom he hath elected, those he hath called, instified, sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and gloryfied:</hi> he answered it is true for those that be elected, but I am reprobate: O beware of blasphemy (sayd I) can reprobate desire to sorrow for the hardnes of his hart? I pray (sayd he) anser
<pb facs="tcp:177877:25"/> me, did not <hi>Saul</hi> loose the spirit of God? answered no: the spirit did depart fom him: but hee lost it not: but till you mee: what spirit that was, which departed from <hi>Saul?</hi> the pirit of grace (sayd he) <hi>alas you are openly deceiued (sayd I)</hi> did not the Lord <hi>say that if <hi>Salamon</hi> did transgresse he would correct him with the sti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es of men but his spirit he would neuer take from him as he did from</hi> Saul: marke: this word (his spirit) sayd he very true (sayd I) and yet<note place="margin">2. Sam. 7. 14. 25.</note> you know Salamon did fall grosly euento idolatry, I pray you what conceit haue you of this word his spirit, which you wish me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member I do meane (sayth he) the spirit of adoption and grace, by Gods spirit, herein you are deceiued (sayd I) <hi>is not the spirrit of fayth: of wisdome: of loue meeknes, and patience, all of these attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted vnto the spirit of God. so the</hi> spirit of wisedome which<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> Saul had, being Gods good spirit was taken from him, the spirit of adoption he had not, and therefore it would not bee taken from him: what spirit then had he left? the spirit of sotishnes dilusion, and ignorance which the Scripture in that same place calleth the euill spirit of God: No (sayth hee) that was the spirit of Sathan, which I haue: not so sayd I: Sathan hath no spirit, but as an instrument to effect the purposes of Gods reuenging euill spirit, which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the first of <hi>Samuel!</hi> 18. 10 and therfore the Lord: <hi>teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs to pray Lead vs not into temptation: and not suffer vs not to be led, to the end we should acknowledg and feare no power, but</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note>
               <hi>the &amp; power spirit of the Lord only:</hi> for there is no power but Gods power onely, Some do vnderstand (sayth he) the word euill in that petition to bee meant of Sathan and what need wee pray against him if hee haue no power? I say Sathan hath a constitution and Creation of enmyty against the Lambe, by reason of that redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that hee wrought to draw mankind out of his hands: which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myty is so deeply infused into our natures by Adam as we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to feare the snares of that captiuity, wherein we are inrenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his allurements: <hi>but for his power, he hath none no not so</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 5</note>
               <hi>much as ouer a pig:</hi> and for that petition to be deliuered frōeuil, we pray that God will rebuke him by those temptations which hee will bring vs into: by giuing vs conquest ouer him: but I pray you (sayth
<pb facs="tcp:177877:26"/> he) was not Salamon an Idolater where was the spirit of God in him? then, I say couered in the ymbers, and greiued exceedingly but not taken away, but to cleare all these doubts <hi>I say</hi> Salamon <hi>was a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igger and a resemblance of Christ, therefore could not loose</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 4. 16</note>
               <hi>the spirit of grace, for Christ will not be resembled in a reprobate</hi> againe he did excell in wisdome all the Kings that euer was before, and since, euen til his dying day. <hi>Therefore neither the spirit of grace, nor wisedome was euer taken from him: agayne he did both Preach the word of truth touching Saluation of the Church and the ende of all momentayno vanytyes euen after he had, racepued sruition of them all,</hi> so questionles God gaue him a good hart of sorrow and repentance for them: and do you not read sayth he <hi>of some that shall plead vnto God at the latter day that they preached in his name did mircales and did cast out Deuils and yet</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 7 14. 15</note>
               <hi>shalbe reiected? yes (sayd I) but</hi> Salamon <hi>had a couenant by speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all promise that God would not forsake him</hi> finally, and therefore passing by his Idolatry <hi>did admit him to build the Temple which he denyed vnto <hi>Dauid</hi> for a smaller offence,</hi> but to let <hi>Salamon</hi> goe and come to our selues how can you answer that speech that you sayd you were Sathan? <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nding the spirit of adoption which made you cry out for a teare? hée answered,</hi> Esau and Saul did feele as much as hee felt, of any goodnes.</p>
            <p>That is not true (sayd I) but the fault is with you that you will not feele, nor confesse when all the company did see you labour and groane for the hardnes of your hart: I did it not in fayth (sayd hee) I adiure you before God and Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus (sayth I) speake the truth. <hi>Was not your desire from a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued spirit:</hi> Yes I thinke so (sayd hee) then sayd I, answer the word of God vnto whom was <hi>Isaih <hi>sent</hi>
               </hi> Isaiah 61. <hi>the spirit of the Lord is vpon mee &amp;c.</hi> Either now acknowledg the Lords comfortable grace and mercy offred vnto you or els you discourage me quite heare I had him at a stand and pausing a little hee sayd where dwell you? will you goe home with mee (sayd I?) will you take charge of mee (sayd hee?) with all my hart (sayd I,) so wee continued together
<pb facs="tcp:177877:26"/> some dayees till hee woulde returne agayne vnto his Father much stronger then hee was I thinke the Lorde: Hee would bewray vnto mee in our particular Conference Sathans instigation to make him lay violent handes vppon himselfe, I asked what scriptures, Sathan did suggest to him? Hee aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered: that place of the Gospell where Christ censureth <hi>gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing offence, with a Milstone to be hanged about his necke and throwne into the Seas:</hi> and to auoyde all offences hee did take this the nearest way to make an ende for he did see nothing, but offence in himselfe out of a blaspheamous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ining spirit, wherewith hee was possessed: Then I demaun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed whether euen in plainenesse and singlenesse, the feare to offend was Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans chiefe bayte or no? and whether the induring his infeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie rather? Hee said little b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t hee could not tell: Then you see said I: Sathan hath more alurements then one, though hee can but wrest the Scripture to giue shew to one onely: for to doe any desperate act, in respect of the smart of Gods affliction, is openly to defie God: to dispute his promises and power: to scorne to bee healed: and to renounce his truth and mercie, who hath bound himselfe both by his <hi>Worde and Oath, that he will be present in all our afflictions: hee will holde vs by the right hand, saying, I haue called thee by thy name, thou art mine: The waters shall not drowne thée; Nor the fire burne thée: <hi>Isayah</hi>
               </hi> 43. 1. 2. 3.</p>
            <p>Now for the other temptation for feare to offend: Sathan you know is a lyar, and so abuseth the Scriptures, for: it is not meant of such as in extreamities, and heauy distractions doe speake weakely, and offensiuely: but rather of su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h as malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously in contempt of the poore (despisinig <hi>God who made them so) doe</hi> scorne their heauie and pittifull plight, by imposing some ouer heauy burden vpon them, or by way of scandall and reproach out of a spirit of malignitie and abiection: I said sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>I</hi> haue a bedfellow (you may see her blessedly and happylie restored, who through the extreamitie of dispayre closed in feare and horror, hath saide thus vnto mee: I
<pb facs="tcp:177877:27"/> pray the M<seg rend="sup">r.</seg>, hold me fast about the hart, or else I shall cry out: and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing neare the paines of a mother: did protest shee fet neither strength, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ope, but she shouldd ee a shame, to her selfe, and all women, but specially to the Gospell in her comfortles trauell, and now listen, and all the world admire: lying silent, and in much hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines. She spoke thus: (Mr said shee) doest thou not remember, in the book<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Martyrs, the story of a man condemned to bee burnt, and al lthe morning before the time of his death, hee complained of the weakenes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Faith, and feare to wound the church by his impatient death a postacy and passing along towards the stake: en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring Smith field: hee cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed his friend vnto him, and cryed aloud <hi>O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugustine he is come▪ he is come:</hi> and so dyed cheerefully and ioyfully: Mr, sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d shee I hope this glouers good will come to mee,<note place="margin">Glouer.</note> will hee not? Yes I warrant thee sweet hart said I▪ as surely as hee hath put th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in remembrance of this story into thy hart, so surely will hee come vnto thee, in the same sort: and so woe vnto mee if I report not the truth of his righteousnes (Viz) That when her paines did approch, she spoke these words <hi>videm!</hi> O Lord thou that didst come vnto thy seruant glouer, help me thy seruant who only hope in thy mercie, and presently she was filled with a streaming ioy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her hart, that the change was strange to beholde in her face, the gesture of her perplexed body, in the ioyfull wordes of her mouth and the teares of her eyes: and yet till the appointed time was come, all the prayers and preachers of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the country, could not preuaile for her reliefe: and great reason for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> should the Lord haue lost his praise, and then it would be said, such a preacher hath recouered Mistris <hi>Sauile,: <hi>For we loue to looke no further then second causes:</hi>
               </hi> no no it is <hi>I say the <hi>the Lord who for my owne sake will doe it, and will not giue my glory to an other:</hi>
               </hi> I <hi>sayah 4. 8.</hi> 10 But admit out of this intollerable feare of hers, any feared offence had broke out in wordes, or cariage, should wee esteeme these amongst those so heauily censured offences? God forbid: But now (said I) to your instigation to lay violent hands vpon your selfe, for a perpetuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke vnto Sathan I demaund? whether such an vnwonted <hi>infandum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>sandum, facinus,</hi> an act in contempt of God, of man, and all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
<pb facs="tcp:177877:27"/> society (euen according to nature only, be a greater offence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the whole world) then all the particular offences whatsoeuer? and my sweet Maples offend not the holy one the mercifull God of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell. The exorable, gentle, pit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iful Lord of heauen and earth▪ <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry not the Lambe to the crosse againe by infid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lity and distrust: Make not the comforter weepe and depart:</hi> But endure for thy crowne take view of the church in the Canticles: <hi>How many grieses</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 5.</note>
               <hi>she endured in seeking her wel beloued passing the dayes and the nights, the watches and the prisons, and whatsoeuer in the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of her sorrow crying out haue you not seene my welbeloued:</hi> Thou wert sure enough man (said I:) <hi>The Angels haue charge of thée, that one hayre of thy head cannot perish: neither thy foot</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10.</note>
               <hi>take hurt: and for proofe thereof who hath rebuked,</hi> and chained vp Sathan all this while? Why ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h hee not preuayled, to make you<note place="margin">Psa 81. 11</note> do this, not nominable haynous act? Who still preserued thee? send<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his seruants to beare thee in their armes, in their harts, and euen in all their desires to bee vnrested by soliciting the Lord for thee? It can neuer bee too often reported that same golden comfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>table place: <hi>They that watte vpon the Lord shall renew their strength</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esay 40 30.</note>
               <hi>their wings shalbe as the winges of Eagles they shall runne and not be weary: They shall walke at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ot be faint: And why do you not proclaime open wars, against that huge deuouring lion.</hi> in the iealousie you haue of the first vowes in Baptisme, wherein you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise to <hi>forsake the world,</hi> the flesh <hi>&amp; the Diuel▪</hi> He would answe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: if I could do this, all were well: would you do it? said I? yes God knoweth said he) and you are sory that you cannot said I. yes indeed (said he) weakly. Come then said I, letus getout of this dark dwelling and claspe our Redeemer, who boweth that we may imbrace him, &amp; imbaseth his face that we may kisse him, <hi>&amp; with all his promises filleth our gripps with ioy &amp; gladnes, sealed vnto vs with yea and Amen</hi> in the deare price of his blood; and I beesech the same Gentle Lord that I may send you home, stronger man then thou comest vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and then the poore sweet creature smiled, and what ioy was that smile vnto my hart, and I had reas: for he departed, and neuer was so very weake after, but endured meekely to the end and gayned
<pb facs="tcp:177877:28"/> happy deliuerance for issue, K. But I pray you my Gentleman: how describe you dispayte, G. I take dispayre to bee the heuyest estate that can befall any man in this mortality: and thus may bee<note place="margin">Dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayre.</note> discribed: <hi>a man forsaken for the time of God: closed in misery, and darknes, depriued of fayth, whereby hée should apprehend the promises of mercy and strength: conceyueth nothing féeleth nothing: but feare and horror by Sathans suggestons, vntil the Lord returne vnto him:</hi> herein Dauids is a liuely pattern Psal, 6 38.<note place="margin">Isaiah. 8.</note> and 112. K. Mee thinkes men should pray instantly to bee deliuered from this kinde of fearefull affliction? Gent. Truly I thinke n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t: the Clay may not say to the potter why hast thou made mee thus? but since <hi>tho order of election, is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed vnto Christ by affliction, and we know the ende holy</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0</note>
               <hi>and for our good let vs leaue euen to the Lord, what way he will pirase to afflict vs:</hi> For hee knoweth best how to make vs for his<note place="margin">Isaiah. 49</note> owne delight, by <hi>healing our brus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and incurable diseases,</hi> and is more carefull <hi>of vs then we or mother can be of our selues:</hi> Therefore as I take it high presumption, to pray for any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler affliction: So I deeme it distrust to suspect his merciful care of vs, in any or all afflictions: Yt is a reason that <hi>Beza <hi>giueth vpon the place of</hi>
               </hi> Ioh. (Viz:) <hi>The Elect cannot sinne fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Iohn 39</note> because saith he, the spirit of God doth correct and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straine their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lydinges:</hi> Wherevpon it is that Caluyn almost in all his Lectures, vpon the Ephesians: <hi>An his prayer doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly desire the Lord for affliction?</hi> Euen so farre, <hi>as that wee beeing made strengthlesse in our selues: May arise by thy strength O Lord, beeing depriued of all pride and perswasion in our selues: For it is thou that woundest, and healest, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est to death, and makest aliue againe:</hi> I should haue fainted saith the Prophet, <hi>But that I sought comfort in thy worde: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy worde and Lawe, is sweeter vnto me, then hony and the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psa. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 9 &amp; 10. part</note>
               <hi>hony combe: O happy time that euer thou diddest afflict me: For whereas before I went astray, now my delight is in thy Law:</hi> But I pray you my Knight how came the Prophet to this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor holde of these promises? K. By his sayth: G. Very
<pb facs="tcp:177877:28"/> well said: But howe came <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee to the life and experience of his Faith? <hi>But by affliction?</hi> For a contemplati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Faith, is but weake in compa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ison of the exercised and practised faith, in the changes of this life: <hi>Wherevpon the wise man biddeth men reioyce in the changes of afflictions: For certainely saith he, as gothe is fined in the fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, so are men acceptable vnto God in the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace of affliction:</hi> And therfore when the Prophet was to encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that huge Philistine Goliah: Samuell 1. 13. From whence did hee gather his encouragement and comfort? But from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of his former deliuer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce in dangers <hi>God (saith he) deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red mee from a Lyon and a Beare:</hi> and therefore I will encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this blaspheaming enemy, in the name of the Lord: Lo his, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer deliuerances, did fraught him with inuincible courage, and so preuailed. K. You say well? but that same example of Caluyns prayer is strange. G. It may bee: vnto them that know not what is required in their practise, for mortification and resurrection: but alow the proportion, that the Lord in afflictions <hi>is no otherwise a iudge, but as a phisition and that his rods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e no otherwise but po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for curing our inherent brusing</hi> and it will follow that as a man in the maladyes of his body, will pray help of the Phisitian &amp; his medicines, &amp; discouer all his secret Leprosies, so and much more, in the spirituall secret view of his Leprosies, congealed in his soule? it is an excellent speach of a father grieued no doubt, and buffet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Sathan, O <hi>Vapul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m Vapul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> saith hee, why? <hi>Fortassis misoributur vapulato:</hi> No doubt, hee was in much affliction al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, Yet desired more as a motiue for the Lords speedy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne and compassion, and indeede it is no small comfort for a man to digest with what a long looking tender eye, and iealous affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Lord watcheth ouer the afflicted: In Ierimiah 30. and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sah</hi> 54. and 57. <hi>The Lord doth threaten vter captiuitie vnto such, as grieue his afflicted ones, and contrariwise comfort &amp; blessing, vnto such as comfort and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lieue them: it is an excellent place, the 3. of <hi>Zachary:</hi> Is not this a brand, but new taken out of the fire and doest thou watch to inflict sorrow vppon him; The Lord rebuke thée Sathan:</hi> And that same fearfull reuenge
<pb facs="tcp:177877:29"/> taken of the Children from grieing Elisha with the words of deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion:<note place="margin">Osey. 2.</note>
               <hi>That the Beares should presently come and deuour them:</hi> Remaineth for a perpetuall and lasting glasse, to view and disgest what tender care the Lord hath ouer such as he hath taken into his owne handes, to correct and make broken harted. K: I could leaue all to tarry with you, and heare you still, but I pray you conclude<note place="margin">2. Kin. 23. 24.</note> from <hi>Osey</hi> the 5. where you say you receiued your wound. G: I am euen now affected much like those exiled sort; who demanded how they should sing the praises of their God in a strange Land? so may I say, beeing exiled from all societye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: and communities: and discouraged by feare of my outward fall in estate: How should I dare to presume to write of this mistery? the highest fourme of all the Schoole: for trayning and conforming the Saints: <hi>But I know whom I haue trusted,</hi> 2 Tim. 12. Therefore help thou mee O Lord, illuminate and <hi>teach me for thy mercie, and they shal know it is thy hand, and that thou Lord hast none it: and hast dealt with me according to thy name, because I am poore and needy &amp; my hartis wouūded within me:</hi> inumerable troubles close me round about, my sinne haue taken holde vpon mee, and feare, and faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, weaken me, by reason I see al my enterprises broken: but thou my Lord who hast the soueraignty ouer all: euen to asswage the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, &amp; billowes of the seas, arise for the deliuerance of the oppressed: <hi>Let not those who call vpon thy name, and haue no hope but in thée the Lord be forgotten for euer: Neither let them be made a by worde vnto the foolish, by dwelling in the shadaw of such a death, and men cast out into the distasting places of vnreformednes, as into</hi> Sodom <hi>Amen.</hi> K. I pray you giue mee this prayer with mee. G Truly I cannot report it againe worde by worde: but now I remember Sir, did I say vnto you, that I receyued my wound from <hi>Osey?</hi> K. Yes: G Then did it not well? for I thought n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t vpon that place, till I was wounded as you tolde mee: That the hurt of sword, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> shott, I is not felt in sight: which is the wound: so I was wounded before I felt the smart: and their seeking remedy I found it in <hi>Osey</hi> where together with the remedy I did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the sm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t, though I must confesse vnto you that I am neuer
<pb facs="tcp:177877:29"/> without feare of some distresse or other: wherevpon I find my selfe censured amongst those wicked: <hi>whose feares fall vpon them:</hi> or from Salamon: Pro. 16. <hi>he that fainteth in aduerstie, his strength was neuer great.</hi> K: The proportion cannot hold: for afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are resembled vnto a schoole or accademy wherein there is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual attendance required of Lectures receiued, and herein pupil or disciples may seeme to faile in his memory, &amp; apprehension and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be accounted non proficient: nor negligent. G. Yet this feare of his vnpreparednes, is frō guilt: and why is he no more vigilant and laborious? So Salamon will taxe him: K. Well: let Salamon haue his right, for that spirit whereby hee writ wrongethno man: It is not denyed but that men should carry about a firme vnshapen preparation vnto the whole will of God: in their attending for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beddyence: But the state of mortalitie hardly affordeth such a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of strength, and renewed change, and haue not you said, that our best strength must stand vppon the acknowledgement of our wantes? What preiudice is it then vnto mee to subscribe Salamons censure that my strength was neuer great? G But may not a man attaine vnto such a measure of perfection, as no alteration shal much dismay him. K Yes I thinke well: for the Prophet Dauid seemeth <hi>to establish a man so growne strong, by fixing his heart vpon God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>as no euill todinges nor alterations whatsoeuer should groatly dismay him:</hi> I thinke that place of Salamon, is not to discourage any that laboureth, but to discouer and condemne the effeminat and delicious daintines, of such as defie the footesteps of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed: and scorne to bee rebuked in their insolent and heady v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surped perswasions: wherein they would grow olde in sinne: and neuer come neare the full age of God, but thinke to passe to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon a bed of downe: but what is this feare to discourage you to conclude, who hath beene broken with one breaking vpon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: and bound vp, and imbraced w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th one mercy after another? your feare therfore is your strength for y<seg rend="sup">•</seg> hath no other vse in you, but to depriue you of the ouer weening of your owne power: The sent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce of Salamon: is an exciting motiue vnto the insolent and car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les like that speech of Peter: <hi>If the righteous shal scarse</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 1. 7</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:177877:30"/>
               <hi>be saued, what shall become of the reprobate?</hi> So from the speech of Salamon, if they who haue indured many afflictions falling weak in one succeeding tryall, shall bee deemed strengthlesse or weake? what shall become of them, that are found vtterly vnprepared? and not acquainted with any common triall? So Salamon touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not you, <hi>who are found trauailing for the recompence of reward, but anounceth you blessed in your feare: yea, at al times:</hi> for you feare not, that the Lord will faile couenant with you, but that your euill fraile hart should displease him, with any the least distrust: is not that your feare? G. Something that way indeede. K. Then in the name of the Lord, presse forward to the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. G: I will and do desire. <hi>That I may procéede euen from that vnshaken worde which shall iudge at the last day:</hi> Iohn 12. and though my feeling be weak by reason of worldly required duties: for my religion, creditors, wife, children, causes, &amp; whatsoeuer wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in my conscience is exercised: and where-vnder I haue endured a long heauy designed rebuke yet as you councelled very well, I will march on lymping as I may, and the Lord will make good that which wanteth: Therefore thus to the 5. of <hi>Osey,</hi> wherin the Lord<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>los<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a 5.</note> expostulateth with the priests, and rulers of Israell, their vnfayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes and wilfull strayings from the worde of his commandement: and in the eleuenth verse where I meane to begin he imbradeth the oppression and brokennes of Ephraim for falling euen against his owne iudgement, being miserably wounded by his transgressions: he did chuse rather to obey the commandement of Ieroboam, then to seeke his reliefe and remedy at the handes of the liuing God: for which though he had Ieraboams commandement yet he could not be healed: <hi>So</hi> Ephraim <hi>proceeded from one errour to another: and sought vnto</hi> As<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r, <hi>and sent vnto</hi> Iacob <hi>King of the</hi> Asserians, <hi>yet could not be cured:</hi> Lo heere was his wound, and incurible bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing: Iere: 30. By conceaued indignitie whereof: the Mr. Phisiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note place="margin">Prisoners cōference Theocca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</note> spoken of in the former conference, <hi>did say he would be as a Lion vnto</hi> Ephrahim, <hi>and as a Lions whelpe vnto</hi> Iuda: <hi>and he would goe away and returne to his place,</hi> how long would he be absent? <hi>till they acknowledge their fault and séeke vnto him:</hi> from
<pb facs="tcp:177877:30"/> this scripture seemeth to bee confirmed that which we haue spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before: That the occasion of our Phisicke and medicines is our wounds: the paine and smart whereof sheweth vs all booteles reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, saue onely at the hand of our gratious healing Phisitian, who letting vs see <hi>that no man can apply one plaister, and yet we will goe strange wayes: Doth tell vs he will be a Lion: at the sight whereof all creatures seeke for safety:</hi> Heere remember the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer conference, where the distressed man taketh hold of the Phisiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and saith: Wilt thou leaue me? Thus farre for the occasion of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction: Now to the cause: verse 15. I wil goe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to my place: to what ende? to make them acknoledge<note place="margin">Cause.</note>
               <hi>their fault, and seeke me saith the Lord:</hi> Lo heere is the cause of the sauing and healing affliction: streaming from that inestima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble loue and care of God: alluring vs by hiding himselfe as the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth from the child, to make vs seeke him that we might be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led see therfore the power and grace of his po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ons? First they work a quite abandoning of all forreyne sought ayde, <hi>euen for finding that superfluity o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iniquity,</hi> spoken of <hi>by</hi> Iames euen as the good Phisitian will purge all superfluous humors befor ehee apply his medicines, and then hee maketh one wounded man speake to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:<note place="margin">The vse.</note>
               <hi>Come let vs returne vnto the Lord, for he hath wounded, and he will binde vp:</hi> So his loue proceedeth not onely to heale vs, but teacheth vs what is the vse of his loue, in these afflictions: that wee must seeke for knowledge, to try and examine our selues: and acknowledge him to be the on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y sauing healling Phisitian: And abandon all the wayes of our former strayings, and endeauour our selues to know the Lord in our whole resigned obedience, giuen vnto the Lords will: Thus farre for the vse: For the ende: <hi>He wil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>store</hi>
               <note place="margin">the end.</note>
               <hi>comfort vnto vs, and vnto as many as pitty vs: He will heale vs soundly, his going forth is prepared as the morning, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isiah. 54.</note>
               <hi>he shall come vnto vs as the very latter raine to the earth:</hi> giue mee your opinion my Knight: Whether I haue confirmed both the<note place="margin">Ier. 30.</note> occasion: The cause: The vse: and end of our happy and blessed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction? The Lord enacted order, for vniting, his affliction, vnto our election, and our election, vnto his nature. K. Indeed you have ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:177877:31"/> sufficiently and comfortably. G. Wel then we will conclude from the last ver: of the: 2 Chap of <hi>Osea. <hi>I will haue mercie vpon her that was not pittied and say vnto them that were not my people, thou art my people and they shall say thou art my God:</hi>
               </hi> And thus my Knight let vs streyne our voices to publish his grations goodnes euen so hie at least as we can see that the applause of our notes, and songs may be caryed vpon the winges of the wind vnto the vtmost quarters of the whole world, and all mouthes filled with the same of his truth and righteousnesse sounding and singing <hi>alleluiah</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:177877:31"/>
            <head>❧ The Authors peraswasion from proofe laying the totall some of the Booke.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>LOng griefe by many chāges taught,</l>
               <l>the authors p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to write:</l>
               <l>This same poore vndigested much</l>
               <l>so take the widd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The dayes and times bee wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nes,</l>
               <l>by heauy conceipts weight:</l>
               <l>The mery neuer thinke time long,</l>
               <l>such is affections sleight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But to preuent that by no change,</l>
               <l>thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime may tast for long:</l>
               <l>Prepare thy thoughts to ioy in smart,</l>
               <l>a preparation strong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In sadnes dwell, and stable rule,</l>
               <l>hold fast and euer feare.</l>
               <l>That natures sleights by plaine deceipt</l>
               <l>away all by will weare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So thus thou wading feedest still,</l>
               <l>vpon desired ende:</l>
               <l>With patience: and ioyst to see,</l>
               <l>how thy twist length doth spend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For truely vaine delights which passe,</l>
               <l>thy time as neuer weary:</l>
               <l>May nature feede, as for the stanle,</l>
               <l>ne making spirit cheary.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There is so strange a difference,</l>
               <l>twixt nature and thy grace:</l>
               <l>That where the sences ioy euen most,</l>
               <l>sure there is snaring place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For sences doe but nature reach,</l>
               <l>but spirit truth aspires:</l>
               <l>For this: the Mr. wages giues,</l>
               <l>vaine bee all other hiers.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The kingdome violence suffer doth,</l>
               <l>and violence is in oyd:</l>
               <l>All entermission is plaine losse,</l>
               <l>and doth thy hold destroy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pray therefore for beleeuing hurt,</l>
               <l>and combates crown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ettaine:</l>
               <l>Abandoning affections fraudes,</l>
               <l>whose ende is euer vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For ease and rest as maine deceipts,</l>
               <l>preuaile with most m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n much:</l>
               <l>But mariage garment neuer lot,</l>
               <l>is sorted vnto such.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O that thou knewst how sweet a thing.</l>
               <l>ta sleepe in Iesus armes.</l>
               <l>Nature should nest of vipers east,</l>
               <l>and den of hugest harmes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Experience reporteth.</l>
               <l>Obedience preuaileth.</l>
               <l>Faith conquereth.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>